{
    "questions": [
        {
            "Question": "Which technique is generally followed when the population is finite?",
            "optionA": "  Area sampling technique ",
            "optionB": "  Purposive sampling technique ",
            "optionC": "  Systematic sampling technique ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSystematic sampling technique is generally followed when the population is finite. ",
            "keyString": "479287s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process not needed in experimental research is",
            "optionA": "  Observation ",
            "optionB": "  Controlling ",
            "optionC": "  Manipulation and replication ",
            "optionD": "  Reference collection ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe process not needed in experimental research is reference collection. ",
            "keyString": "479316s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a non-probability sample?",
            "optionA": "  Quota sample ",
            "optionB": "  Simple random sample ",
            "optionC": "  Purposive sample ",
            "optionD": "  (a) and (c) both of them ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuota sample and purposive sample is a non-probability sample. ",
            "keyString": "479329s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The experimental study is based on the law of",
            "optionA": "  Single variable ",
            "optionB": "  Replication ",
            "optionC": "  Occupation ",
            "optionD": "  Interest in the subject ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe experimental study is based on the law of single variable. ",
            "keyString": "479340s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A researcher divides his population into groups and fixes the size of the sample from each group. It is an example of",
            "optionA": "  Stratified sample ",
            "optionB": "  Quota sample ",
            "optionC": "  Cluster sample ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA researcher divides his population into groups and fixes the size of the sample from each group. It is an example of quota sample. ",
            "keyString": "479349s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main characteristic of scientific research is :",
            "optionA": "  Empirical ",
            "optionB": "  Theoretical ",
            "optionC": "  Experimental ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main characteristic of scientific research is empirical, theoretical and experimental. ",
            "keyString": "513268s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A null hypothesis is",
            "optionA": "  When there is no difference between the variables ",
            "optionB": "  The same as research hypothesis ",
            "optionC": "  Subjective in nature ",
            "optionD": "  When there is difference between the variables ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA null hypothesis is when there is no difference between the variables. ",
            "keyString": "513296s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The research which is exploring new facts through the study of the past is called",
            "optionA": "  Philosophical research ",
            "optionB": "  Historical research ",
            "optionC": "  Mythological research ",
            "optionD": "  Content analysis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe research which is exploring new facts through the study of the past is called historical research. ",
            "keyString": "513309s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Manipulation is always a part of",
            "optionA": "  Historical research ",
            "optionB": "  Fundamental research ",
            "optionC": "  Descriptive research ",
            "optionD": "  Experimental research ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tManipulation is always a part of experimental research. ",
            "keyString": "513320s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which correlation co-efficient best explains the relationship between creativity and intelligence?",
            "optionA": "  1.00 ",
            "optionB": "  0.6 ",
            "optionC": "  0.5 ",
            "optionD": "  0.3 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t1.00 correlation co-efficient best explains the relationship between creativity and intelligence. ",
            "keyString": "513331s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "It is advantage of giving home work that students",
            "optionA": "  Remain busy at home ",
            "optionB": "  Study at home ",
            "optionC": "  May be checked for their progress ",
            "optionD": "  May develop habit of self-study ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHomework helps teachers determine how well the lessons are being understood by their students. Homework teaches students how to problem solve. Homework gives student another opportunity to review class material. ",
            "keyString": "547156s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher has serious defect if he/she",
            "optionA": "  Is physically handicapped ",
            "optionB": "  Belongs to low socio-economic status ",
            "optionC": "  Has weak personality ",
            "optionD": "  Has immature mental development ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher has serious defect if he/she has immature mental development. ",
            "keyString": "547184s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The success of teacher is",
            "optionA": "  High achievement of students ",
            "optionB": "  Good traits of his/her personality ",
            "optionC": "  His/her good teaching ",
            "optionD": "  His/her good character ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA successful teacher is the teacher whom the students remember with great pleasure, knows how to teach well in such a way that each student understands. It is that teacher who teaches clearly, briefly and on the subject. ",
            "keyString": "547196s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A deepawali fair is being organized in your school. What would you like to do ?",
            "optionA": "  Only to visit the fair ",
            "optionB": "  To take part in function ",
            "optionC": "  To take a shop to sell something ",
            "optionD": "  To distribute free water to visitors ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo take part in function. ",
            "keyString": "547206s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important trait of a student is",
            "optionA": "  Sense of responsibility ",
            "optionB": "  To speak truth ",
            "optionC": "  Co-operation ",
            "optionD": "  Obedience ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tObedience is the most important trait of a student. ",
            "keyString": "547217s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "You like teaching profession because",
            "optionA": "  It has less responsibility ",
            "optionB": "  You are interested in it ",
            "optionC": "  It is easy ",
            "optionD": "  It provide you more holidays ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou like teaching profession because you are interested in it. ",
            "keyString": "580072s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How the students should be motivated to get success in life?",
            "optionA": "  Selected study ",
            "optionB": "  Incidental study ",
            "optionC": "  Intensive study ",
            "optionD": "  Learning by recitation ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIntensive study is the way by which students should be motivated to get success in life. ",
            "keyString": "580101s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In context of the habit of absenteeism of student",
            "optionA": "  The principal and parents should get worried ",
            "optionB": "  The officials of the schools should take action against them as per school's discipline ",
            "optionC": "  The teachers should take it as a serious problem ",
            "optionD": "  They should be given less priority in the class room in relation to regular students ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn context of the habit of absenteeism of student the teachers should take it as a serious problem. ",
            "keyString": "580113s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To whom the responsibility of organisation of curricular activities should be stored with?",
            "optionA": "  The principal ",
            "optionB": "  The teacher who is appointed for this work ",
            "optionC": "  The teachers who take interest in it ",
            "optionD": "  All the teachers ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe responsibility of organisation of curricular activities should be stored with the principal. ",
            "keyString": "580124s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the students try to solve the questions in some different way as taught by the teacher from prescribed books, then these students should be",
            "optionA": "  Discouraged to consult some other books on the subject ",
            "optionB": "  Encouraged to consult some other books on the subject ",
            "optionC": "  Suggested to talk with their teacher after the period ",
            "optionD": "  Suggested to follow the class room notes in order to get good mark in the examination ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThese students should be encouraged to consult some other books on the subject. ",
            "keyString": "580134s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To maintain interest among students in class, a teacher should",
            "optionA": "  Use blackboard ",
            "optionB": "  Discuss ",
            "optionC": "  Tell stories ",
            "optionD": "  Ask question ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo maintain interest among students in class, a teacher should ask question. ",
            "keyString": "613703s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The purpose of new education policy is",
            "optionA": "  To provide equal opportunity of education to all ",
            "optionB": "  To improve the whole education system ",
            "optionC": "  To link the education with employment ",
            "optionD": "  To delink the degree with education ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Policy envisages a new curricular and pedagogical structure for school education that is responsive and relevant to the needs and interests of learners at different stages of their development. This Policy aims to shape an education system that benefits all of India's children. ",
            "keyString": "613731s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To raise the standard of education, it is necessary",
            "optionA": "  To evaluate students continuously ",
            "optionB": "  To give high salary to teachers ",
            "optionC": "  To revise curriculum ",
            "optionD": "  To make good school building ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo raise the standard of education, it is necessary to evaluate students continuously. ",
            "keyString": "613744s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is most important for a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  To maintain discipline in class ",
            "optionB": "  To be punctual in class ",
            "optionC": "  To remove difficulties of students ",
            "optionD": "  To be good orator ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t To remove difficulties of students. ",
            "keyString": "613756s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why students should play games in school?",
            "optionA": "  It makes them physically strong ",
            "optionB": "  It makes work easier for teachers ",
            "optionC": "  It helps in passing time ",
            "optionD": "  It develops co-operation and physical balance ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGames develops co-operation and physical balance. ",
            "keyString": "613767s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A research paper is a brief report of research work based on",
            "optionA": "  Primary data only ",
            "optionB": "  Secondary data only ",
            "optionC": "  Both primary and secondary data ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA research paper is a brief report of research work based on both primary and secondary data. ",
            "keyString": "664888s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Newton gave three basic laws of motion. This research is categorized as",
            "optionA": "  Descriptive research ",
            "optionB": "  Sample survey ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental research ",
            "optionD": "  Applied research ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNewton gave three basic laws of motion. This research is categorized as fundamental research. ",
            "keyString": "664921s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the process of conducting research 'formulation of hypothesis' is followed by",
            "optionA": "  Statement of objectives ",
            "optionB": "  Analysis of data ",
            "optionC": "  Selection of research tools ",
            "optionD": "  Collection of data ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the process of conducting research 'formulation of hypothesis' is followed by selection of research tools. ",
            "keyString": "664934s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The essential qualities of a researcher are",
            "optionA": "  Spirit of free enquiry ",
            "optionB": "  Reliance on observation and evidence ",
            "optionC": "  Systematization or theorizing of knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "664945s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following variables cannot be expressed in quantitative terms?",
            "optionA": "  Socio-economic status ",
            "optionB": "  Marital status ",
            "optionC": "  Numerical aptitude ",
            "optionD": "  Professional attitude ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProfessional attitude cannot be expressed in quantitative terms. ",
            "keyString": "664955s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The purpose of basic education scheme is",
            "optionA": "  Universalization of primary education ",
            "optionB": "  To vocationalise the education ",
            "optionC": "  To fulfil basic need of persons through education ",
            "optionD": "  To make education compulsory for all ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe purpose of basic education scheme is to fulfil basic need of persons through education. ",
            "keyString": "697612s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "You are teaching a topic in class and a student ask a question unrelated to the topic. What will you do ?",
            "optionA": "  You will allow him to ask unrelated question ",
            "optionB": "  You will not allow him to ask unrelated question ",
            "optionC": "  You will consider it indiscipline and punish him ",
            "optionD": "  You will answer the question after the class ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will answer the question after the class. ",
            "keyString": "697639s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If you are unable to get a job of teacher, then you will",
            "optionA": "  Start giving tuition at home ",
            "optionB": "  Remain at home till you get a job ",
            "optionC": "  Take some another job ",
            "optionD": "  Continue applying for teaching ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf you are unable to get a job of teacher, then you will continue applying for teaching. ",
            "keyString": "697652s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher can motivate the students by",
            "optionA": "  Giving suitable prizes ",
            "optionB": "  Giving proper guidance ",
            "optionC": "  Giving examples ",
            "optionD": "  Delivering speech in class ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher can motivate the students by giving suitable prizes. ",
            "keyString": "697663s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a student does not pay any respect to you, then you will",
            "optionA": "  Ignore him ",
            "optionB": "  Award less marks in examination ",
            "optionC": "  Talk to his/her parents ",
            "optionD": "  Rebuke him ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a student does not pay any respect to you, then you will ignore him. ",
            "keyString": "697674s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The review of the related study is important while undertaking a research because",
            "optionA": "  It avoids repetition or duplication ",
            "optionB": "  It helps in understanding the gaps ",
            "optionC": "  It helps the researcher not to draw illogical conclusions ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe review of the related study is important while undertaking a research because it avoids repetition or duplication, it helps in understanding the gaps and it helps the researcher not to draw illogical conclusions. ",
            "keyString": "731418s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The historical research is different from experimental research in the process of",
            "optionA": "  Replication ",
            "optionB": "  Formulation of the hypothesis ",
            "optionC": "  The hypothesis testing ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe historical research is different from experimental research in the process of replication, formulation of the hypothesis and the hypothesis testing. ",
            "keyString": "731448s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The other name of independent variable for an experimental  research  is/are",
            "optionA": "  Treatment variable ",
            "optionB": "  Experimental variable ",
            "optionC": "  Manipulated variable ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe other name of independent variable for an experimental research is/are treatment variable, experimental variable and manipulated variable. ",
            "keyString": "731461s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If you are doing experiment on a large group of sample which method of controlling will you adopt?",
            "optionA": "  Matching ",
            "optionB": "  Randomisation ",
            "optionC": "  Elimination and matching ?both of them ",
            "optionD": "  Elimination only ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRandomisation should be adopted. ",
            "keyString": "731473s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Seeing a very big rally it was reported that congress will win the election. The conclusion was based on",
            "optionA": "  Random sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Cluster sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Systematic sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Purposive sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeeing a very big rally it was reported that congress will win the election. The conclusion was based on purposive sampling. ",
            "keyString": "731485s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The aim of national council for teacher education is",
            "optionA": "  To open college of education ",
            "optionB": "  To promote research in education ",
            "optionC": "  To maintain standards in colleges of education ",
            "optionD": "  To provide grant to colleges of education ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe aim of national council for teacher education is to maintain standards in colleges of education. ",
            "keyString": "781533s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kindergarten system of education was contributed by",
            "optionA": "  T. P. Nunn ",
            "optionB": "  Spencer ",
            "optionC": "  Froebel ",
            "optionD": "  Montessori ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKindergarten system of education was contributed by Froebel. ",
            "keyString": "781566s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "'National council of educational research and training' was established in",
            "optionA": "  1961 ",
            "optionB": "  1962 ",
            "optionC": "  1963 ",
            "optionD": "  1964 ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) is an autonomous organisation of the Government of India which was established in 1961 as a literary, scientific and charitable Society under the Societies' Registration Act (Act XXI of 1860). ",
            "keyString": "781580s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Essay type test are not reliable because",
            "optionA": "  Their answers are different ",
            "optionB": "  Their results are different ",
            "optionC": "  Their checking is affected by examiner's mood ",
            "optionD": "  Their responding styles are different ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEssay type test are not reliable because their checking is affected by examiner's mood. ",
            "keyString": "781592s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A guardian never comes to see you in school. You will",
            "optionA": "  Ignore the child ",
            "optionB": "  Write to the guardian ",
            "optionC": "  Go to meet him yourself ",
            "optionD": "  Start punishing the child ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGo to meet him yourself. ",
            "keyString": "781603s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a form of evaluation research?",
            "optionA": "  Need assessment ",
            "optionB": "  Process evaluation ",
            "optionC": "  Context evaluation ",
            "optionD": "  Programme evaluation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProgramme evaluation is not a form of evaluation research. ",
            "keyString": "815271s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is the method of data collection?",
            "optionA": "  Warranty cards ",
            "optionB": "  Distributor or store audits ",
            "optionC": "  Pantry audits ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "815303s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a basic component of research?",
            "optionA": "  We can know nature ",
            "optionB": "  All natural phenomena have unnatural causes ",
            "optionC": "  Knowledge is better than ignorance ",
            "optionD": "  Knowledge is  derived from observation of nature ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll natural phenomena have unnatural causes. ",
            "keyString": "815319s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is wrong regarding inductive generalizations?",
            "optionA": "  They are based on observed facts and realistic foundation ",
            "optionB": "  It is scientific in character and some of the important theorems of the physical and social sciences have been developed through this method ",
            "optionC": "  It is helpful in finding out the material truth ",
            "optionD": "  It is easy, cost effective and time saving method ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is easy, cost effective and time saving method. ",
            "keyString": "815331s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A concept is a word or a phrase which symbolizes the phenomenon and helps to communicate the finding. Which fact about the concept is wrong?",
            "optionA": "  It is similar to an the same thing as a fact ",
            "optionB": "  It is abstracted from the sense perceptions ",
            "optionC": "  They are logical constructs created from the sense impressions or complex experiences ",
            "optionD": "  It should not be confusing ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt is similar to an the same thing as a fact. ",
            "keyString": "815342s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statement is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Discoveries are researches ",
            "optionB": "  Researches lead to discovery ",
            "optionC": "  Invention and research are related ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearches lead to discovery. ",
            "keyString": "885273s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a student is constantly rubbing his eyes and is inattentive during blackboard work, he is having",
            "optionA": "  Adjustment problem ",
            "optionB": "  Hearing problem ",
            "optionC": "  Visual problem ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a student is constantly rubbing his eyes and is inattentive during blackboard work, he is having visual problem. ",
            "keyString": "885302s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The professional requirement of a teacher as explained in the UNESCO publication is/are",
            "optionA": "  Mastery over the subject and competency for teaching ",
            "optionB": "  Innovativeness in approach and teaching strategies ",
            "optionC": "  Justice to the profession ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe professional requirement of a teacher as explained in the UNESCO publication is/are mastery over the subject and competency for teaching, innovativeness in approach and teaching strategies and justice to the profession. ",
            "keyString": "885314s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Kindergarten (kg) system of education is indebted to",
            "optionA": "  Dewey ",
            "optionB": "  Froebel ",
            "optionC": "  Plato ",
            "optionD": "  Spencer ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKindergarten (kg) system of education is indebted to Froebel. ",
            "keyString": "885325s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following must be the qualities of teacher except?",
            "optionA": "  Patience and tolerance ",
            "optionB": "  Sweet, polite and clear voice ",
            "optionC": "  Superstitions ",
            "optionD": "  Good communication skill ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe following must be the qualities of teacher except superstitions. ",
            "keyString": "885335s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The idea of basic education is propounded by",
            "optionA": "  Dr. Zakir Hussain ",
            "optionB": "  Dr. Rajendra Prasad ",
            "optionC": "  Mahatma Gandhi ",
            "optionD": "  Rabindranath Tagore ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe idea of basic education is propounded by Mahatma Gandhi. ",
            "keyString": "917880s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important indicator of quality of education in a school is",
            "optionA": "  Infrastructural facilities of a school ",
            "optionB": "  Classroom system ",
            "optionC": "  Text-books and teaching-learning material ",
            "optionD": "  Student achievement level ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important indicator of quality of education in a school is Student achievement level. ",
            "keyString": "917907s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best remedy of the student's problems related with learning is",
            "optionA": "  Suggestion for hard work ",
            "optionB": "  Supervised study in library ",
            "optionC": "  Suggestion for private tuition ",
            "optionD": "  Diagnostic teaching ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe best remedy of the student's problems related with learning is diagnostic teaching. ",
            "keyString": "917921s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The in-service teacher' training can be made more effective by",
            "optionA": "  Using training package which in well prepared in advance ",
            "optionB": "  Making it a residential programme ",
            "optionC": "  Using co-operative approach ",
            "optionD": "  Practicing training follow up procedures ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe in-service teacher' training can be made more effective by practicing training follow up procedures. ",
            "keyString": "917932s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How a teacher should behave with the students",
            "optionA": "  General ",
            "optionB": "  Father ",
            "optionC": "  Friend ",
            "optionD": "  Leader ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher should behave with the students like a leader. ",
            "keyString": "917943s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The experienced teachers do not require the detailed lesson plan of a topic because",
            "optionA": "  They can teach in a good manner without its help ",
            "optionB": "  The number of curious students is very poor in the class ",
            "optionC": "  When they commit some mistake, they do not face any challenge from their students ",
            "optionD": "  They can equip themselves with brief outline as they gain specialisation in it through experience ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey can equip themselves with brief outline as they gain specialisation in it through experience. ",
            "keyString": "951149s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The problem of drop-out in which students leave their schooling in early years can be tackled in a better way through",
            "optionA": "  Reduction of the weight of curriculum ",
            "optionB": "  Sympathy of teachers ",
            "optionC": "  Attractive environment of the school ",
            "optionD": "  Encouragement of the students ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe problem of drop-out in which students leave their schooling in early years can be tackled in a better way through encouragement of the students. ",
            "keyString": "951180s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The ideal teacher",
            "optionA": "  Teaches the whole curriculum ",
            "optionB": "  Helps his students in learning ",
            "optionC": "  Is a friend, philosopher and guide ",
            "optionD": "  Maintains good discipline ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe ideal teacher is a friend, philosopher and guide. ",
            "keyString": "951194s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The aim of education should be",
            "optionA": "  To develop vocational skills in the students ",
            "optionB": "  To develop social awareness in the students ",
            "optionC": "  To prepare the students for examination ",
            "optionD": "  To prepare the students for practical life ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe aim of education should be to prepare the students for practical life. ",
            "keyString": "951205s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best method of checking student's homework is",
            "optionA": "  To assign it to intelligent students of the class ",
            "optionB": "  To check the answers in the class in group manner ",
            "optionC": "  To check them with the help of specimen answer ",
            "optionD": "  To check by the teacher himself in a regular way ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe best method of checking student's homework is to check by the teacher himself in a regular way. ",
            "keyString": "951216s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following institutions is responsible for the implementation of reforms in teaching profession?",
            "optionA": "  University grants commission ",
            "optionB": "  National council for teacher's education ",
            "optionC": "  National council for educational research and training ",
            "optionD": "  National institute of educational planning and administration ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNational institute of educational planning and administration is responsible for the implementation of reforms in teaching profession. ",
            "keyString": "984448s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A serious minded teacher as a rule:",
            "optionA": "  Allows the mistakes to be committed and explains how to minimise those mistakes ",
            "optionB": "  Never allows mistakes on the part of his students ",
            "optionC": "  Takes all precaution so that students never commit mistakes ",
            "optionD": "  Should mildly punish students who commit mistakes ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAllows the mistakes to be committed and explains how to minimise those mistakes. ",
            "keyString": "984478s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of your student is too poor to buy a book. How will you help him?",
            "optionA": "  You will purchase the book ",
            "optionB": "  You will collect a fund from others for this purpose ",
            "optionC": "  You will provide the books from library ",
            "optionD": "  You will request the institute administration to make a policy for helping such students ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will provide the books from library. ",
            "keyString": "984490s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Objective type questions are not helpful in testing",
            "optionA": "  Student's knowledge level of subject matter ",
            "optionB": "  Student's ability to describe and explain things ",
            "optionC": "  Student's ability of writing and expression ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above. ",
            "keyString": "984501s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is responsible for uniformity in curriculum at higher level in India?",
            "optionA": "  University grants commission ",
            "optionB": "  National council for educational research and training ",
            "optionC": "  Human resource development ministry ",
            "optionD": "  All India council for technical education ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUniversity grants commission is responsible for uniformity in curriculum at higher level in India. ",
            "keyString": "984510s34m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Most important work of teacher is",
            "optionA": "  To organize teaching work ",
            "optionB": "  To deliver lecture in class ",
            "optionC": "  To take care of children ",
            "optionD": "  To evaluate the students ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMost important work of teacher is to organize teaching work. ",
            "keyString": "16516s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher should be",
            "optionA": "  Honest ",
            "optionB": "  Diligent ",
            "optionC": "  Dutiful ",
            "optionD": "  Punctual ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher should be dutiful. ",
            "keyString": "16545s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Environmental education should be taught in schools because",
            "optionA": "  It will affect environmental pollution ",
            "optionB": "  It is important part of life ",
            "optionC": "  It will provide job to teachers ",
            "optionD": "  We cannot escape from environment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEnvironmental education helps students understand how their decisions and actions affect the environment, builds knowledge and skills necessary to address complex environmental issues, as well as ways we can take action to keep our environment healthy and sustainable for the future. ",
            "keyString": "16557s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At primary level, it is better to teach in mother language because",
            "optionA": "  It develops self-confidence in children ",
            "optionB": "  It makes learning easy ",
            "optionC": "  It is helpful in intellectual development ",
            "optionD": "  It helps children in learning in natural atmosphere ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt primary level, it is better to teach in mother language because it helps children in learning in natural atmosphere. ",
            "keyString": "16569s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Women are better teacher at primary level because",
            "optionA": "  They behave more patiently with children ",
            "optionB": "  They are ready to work with low salary ",
            "optionC": "  Higher qualification is not needed in this profession ",
            "optionD": "  They have less chances in other profession ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAbility to understand students' mental and emotional needs make women a better choice for teachers in primary schools. They have a better understanding of child psychology. ",
            "keyString": "16580s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Failure of the teacher to communicate its ideas well to the students may result in",
            "optionA": "  Classroom indiscipline ",
            "optionB": "  Loss of student's interest in hot topic being taught ",
            "optionC": "  Increase in number of absentees in the class ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "49566s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a group of students enter your room and abuse you and behave violently with you, at that time how you would control your emotions?",
            "optionA": "  You will react in a similar fashion and try to assault them physically ",
            "optionB": "  First, you will try to pacify their emotions and then ask politely about their behaviour ",
            "optionC": "  You will feel ashamed among your teachers community ",
            "optionD": "  You will report the case to the principal with recommendation of punitive measures ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFirst, you will try to pacify their emotions and then ask politely about their behaviour. ",
            "keyString": "49596s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is the reason behind the adoption of grade system instead of our old marks system?",
            "optionA": "  It will improve the quality of assessment ",
            "optionB": "  It will improve teacher student relationship ",
            "optionC": "  It will eliminate the differentiation between students on marks basis ",
            "optionD": "  Grading system is easier than marks system ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt will eliminate the differentiation between students on marks basis. ",
            "keyString": "49609s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why do you support the five stage method of Herbart?",
            "optionA": "  In this there is no scope for individual diversity of students ",
            "optionB": "  Under this, generalisation is not required to be done while teaching subjects like language, history, geography etc ",
            "optionC": "  In this method, it is difficult to make co-ordination between various subjects ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "49620s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following are true about teaching?",
            "optionA": "  Teaching is dynamic in nature ",
            "optionB": "  Teaching is a process ",
            "optionC": "  It changes its concept with time and place ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeaching is dynamic in nature, teaching is a process and it changes its concept with time and place. ",
            "keyString": "49630s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The function of a teacher is in the order of :",
            "optionA": "  Guiding the child, helping him towards progress and evaluation ",
            "optionB": "  Checking homework, guiding him and assigning further task ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe function of a teacher is in the order of guiding the child, helping him towards progress and evaluation. ",
            "keyString": "81899s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Classroom discipline can be maintained effectively by:",
            "optionA": "  Knowing the cause of indiscipline and handling it with stern hand ",
            "optionB": "  Providing a programme which is according to need and interest of pupils ",
            "optionC": "  By giving punishment for even smallest sins ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProviding a programme which is according to need and interest of pupils. ",
            "keyString": "81926s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following can be the effect of meteorite impact?",
            "optionA": "  Massive earthquake ",
            "optionB": "  Dust in atmosphere ",
            "optionC": "  Widespread wildfire ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMassive earthquake, dust in atmosphere and widespread wildfire can be the effect of meteorite impact. ",
            "keyString": "81938s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Central soil salinity research institute is situated at",
            "optionA": "  Kasaragod ",
            "optionB": "  Karnal ",
            "optionC": "  Gulmarg ",
            "optionD": "  Gwalior ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCentral soil salinity research institute is situated at Karnal. ",
            "keyString": "81949s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which satellite channel uses the ad line, knowing is everything?",
            "optionA": "  BBC world ",
            "optionB": "  Star ",
            "optionC": "  Sony ",
            "optionD": "  Zee ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBBC world ad line is knowing is everything. ",
            "keyString": "81959s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A research problem is feasible only when it is",
            "optionA": "  It is researchable ",
            "optionB": "  It  is new and adds something to knowledge ",
            "optionC": "  It has utility and relevance ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "115642s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A researcher selects a probability sample of 100 out of the total population. It is",
            "optionA": "  A cluster sample ",
            "optionB": "  A random sample ",
            "optionC": "  A stratified sample ",
            "optionD": "  A systematic sample ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA researcher selects a probability sample of 100 out of the total population. It is a random sample. ",
            "keyString": "115669s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Studying the social status of a population, a researcher concluded that Mr. S is socially backward. His conclusion is",
            "optionA": "  Wrong ",
            "optionB": "  Rights ",
            "optionC": "  Inaccurate ",
            "optionD": "  Biased ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudying the social status of a population, a researcher concluded that Mr. S is socially backward. His conclusion is inacurrate. ",
            "keyString": "115684s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Generalised conclusion on the basis of a sample is technically known as",
            "optionA": "  Statistical inference of external validity of the research ",
            "optionB": "  Data analysis and interpretation ",
            "optionC": "  Parameter inference ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGeneralised conclusion on the basis of a sample is technically known as statistical inference of external validity of the research. ",
            "keyString": "115694s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A good hypothesis should be",
            "optionA": "  Precise specific and consistent with most known facts ",
            "optionB": "  Formulated in such a way that it can be tested by data ",
            "optionC": "  Of limited scope and should not have global significance ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "115704s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If in a research independent variables cannot be manipulated then it is known as",
            "optionA": "  Experimental research ",
            "optionB": "  Non-experimental research ",
            "optionC": "  Pure or fundamental research ",
            "optionD": "  Exploratory research ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf in a research independent variables cannot be manipulated then it is known as non- experimental research. ",
            "keyString": "165905s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a characteristic of research?",
            "optionA": "  Systematic ",
            "optionB": "  Objective ",
            "optionC": "  Logical ",
            "optionD": "  Perspective ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPerspective is not a characteristic of research. ",
            "keyString": "165933s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that members of the same species are not alike?",
            "optionA": "  Darwin ",
            "optionB": "  Herber ",
            "optionC": "  Best ",
            "optionD": "  Good ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDarwin said that members of the same species are not alike. ",
            "keyString": "165944s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Certificate for copyright waiver is generally given in",
            "optionA": "  Thesis writing ",
            "optionB": "  Paper ",
            "optionC": "  Article ",
            "optionD": "  Books ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCertificate for copyright waiver is generally given in thesis writing. ",
            "keyString": "165955s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Logic of induction is very close to",
            "optionA": "  Logic of sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Logic of observation ",
            "optionC": "  Logic of controlled variables ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tLogic of induction is very close to logic of sampling.",
            "keyString": "165966s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Scientific elucidation is the fundamental objective of which research characteristic?",
            "optionA": "  Basic research ",
            "optionB": "  Long term research ",
            "optionC": "  Naturalistic inquiry ",
            "optionD": "  Holistic perspective ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tScientific elucidation is the fundamental objective of basic research. ",
            "keyString": "199068s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which form of research is concerned with describing, explaining and predicting natural phenomena and relies only on experience and observation?",
            "optionA": "  Quantitative research ",
            "optionB": "  Qualitative research ",
            "optionC": "  Applied research ",
            "optionD": "  Fundamental research ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental research is concerned with describing, explaining and predicting natural phenomena and relies only on experience and observation. ",
            "keyString": "199097s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a problem associated with observational studies?",
            "optionA": "  The main conclusion may be invalid because of the confounding effects of uncontrolled variables ",
            "optionB": "  Estimates may be biased because of non-random sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Observations have to be taken on groups of individuals rather than on individuals themselves ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNone of the above ",
            "keyString": "199110s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following research method requires a researcher to freely pick up a problem, redesign the enquiry as he proceeds and is prepared to conceptualize as he wishes?",
            "optionA": "  Historical research ",
            "optionB": "  Conclusion-oriented research ",
            "optionC": "  Decision-oriented research ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tConclusion-oriented research requires a researcher to freely pick up a problem, redesign the enquiry as he proceeds and is prepared to conceptualize as he wishes. ",
            "keyString": "199120s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following approach is not used for developing a working hypothesis?",
            "optionA": "  Discussion with colleagues and experts about the problem, its origin and objectives in seeking a solution ",
            "optionB": "  Examination of data and records, if available, concerning the problem for possible trends, peculiarities and other clues ",
            "optionC": "  Review of similar studies in the area or of the studies on similar problems ",
            "optionD": "  Following the traditional trend ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFollowing the traditional trend is not used for developing a working hypothesis. ",
            "keyString": "199131s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following sampling methods is based on probability?",
            "optionA": "  Convenience sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Quota sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Judgement sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Stratified sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStratified sampling is based on probability. ",
            "keyString": "225515s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Identify the incorrect statement :",
            "optionA": "  A hypothesis is made on the basis of limited evidence as a starting point for further investigations ",
            "optionB": "  A hypothesis is a basis for reasoning without any assumption of its truth ",
            "optionC": "  Hypothesis is a proposed explanation for a phenomenon ",
            "optionD": "  Scientific hypothesis is a scientific theory ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHypothesis is a proposed explanation for a phenomenon. ",
            "keyString": "225542s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A research paper",
            "optionA": "  Is a compilation of information on a topic ",
            "optionB": "  Contains original research as deemed by the author ",
            "optionC": "  Contains peer-reviewed original research or evaluation of research conducted by others ",
            "optionD": "  Can be published in more than one journal ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA research paper contains peer-reviewed original research or evaluation of research conducted by others. ",
            "keyString": "225555s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following articles of the constitution of India safeguards the rights of minorities to establish and run educational institutions of their own liking?",
            "optionA": "  Article 19 ",
            "optionB": "  Article 29 ",
            "optionC": "  Article 30 ",
            "optionD": "  Article 31 ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArticle 30 safeguards the rights of minorities to establish and run educational institutions of their own liking. ",
            "keyString": "258835s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The maximum emission of pollutants from fuel sources in India is caused by :",
            "optionA": "  Coal ",
            "optionB": "  Firewood ",
            "optionC": "  Refuse burning ",
            "optionD": "  Vegetable waste product ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe maximum emission of pollutants from fuel sources in India is caused by refuse burning. ",
            "keyString": "258863s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the most important characteristic of open book examination system?",
            "optionA": "  Students become serious ",
            "optionB": "  It improves attendance in the classroom ",
            "optionC": "  It reduces examination anxiety amongst students ",
            "optionD": "  It compels students to think ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt compels students to think. ",
            "keyString": "258877s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A satisfactory quantitative method should not possess one of the following qualities :",
            "optionA": "  Appropriateness ",
            "optionB": "  Measurability ",
            "optionC": "  Comparability ",
            "optionD": "  Flexibility ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA satisfactory quantitative method should not possess flexibility. ",
            "keyString": "258888s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Attributes of objects, events or things which can be measured are called",
            "optionA": "  Qualitative measure ",
            "optionB": "  Data ",
            "optionC": "  Variables ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAttributes of objects, events or things which can be measured are called variables. ",
            "keyString": "258900s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Professors need to study educational philosophy mainly because",
            "optionA": "  Most professors know nothing about educational philosophy ",
            "optionB": "  Most professors follow a wrong philosophy ",
            "optionC": "  They may improve their work by classifying their philosophy ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tProfessors need to study educational philosophy mainly because they may improve their work by classifying their philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "310029s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "On which of the following statements there is consensus among educators?",
            "optionA": "  Disciplinary cases should be sent to the principal only when other means have failed ",
            "optionB": "  Disciplinary cases should never be sent to principal?s office ",
            "optionC": "  Disciplinary cases should be totally neglected in the class ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDisciplinary cases should be sent to the principal only when other means have failed. ",
            "keyString": "310062s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A competent teacher must have a sound knowledge about:",
            "optionA": "  Practice, concept, theory and research ",
            "optionB": "  Theory, research, practice and concepts ",
            "optionC": "  Concept, theory, practice and research ",
            "optionD": "  Research, practice, concept and theory ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA competent teacher must have a sound knowledge about: concept, theory, practice and research. ",
            "keyString": "310075s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Below are given some probable characteristics of an ineffective teacher, which of the following is most likely to be characterised the ineffective teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Emphasis upon standards ",
            "optionB": "  Emphasis upon pupil discussion in the clarification of group's goals ",
            "optionC": "  Emphasis upon the control of immediate situation ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmphasis upon the control of immediate situation.",
            "keyString": "310087s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Maximum participation of students is possible in teaching through",
            "optionA": "  Lecture method ",
            "optionB": "  Discussion method ",
            "optionC": "  Textbook method ",
            "optionD": "  Audi-visual aids ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMaximum participation of students is possible in teaching through discussion method. ",
            "keyString": "310098s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Freedom if press as such",
            "optionA": "  Has been guaranteed by the constitution ",
            "optionB": "  Has not been expressly guaranteed by the constitution ",
            "optionC": "  Has been given only to selected institutions ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFreedom if press as such has not been expressly guaranteed by the constitution. ",
            "keyString": "344311s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The planning commission of India is",
            "optionA": "  Tripura ",
            "optionB": "  Meghalaya ",
            "optionC": "  Mizoram ",
            "optionD": "  Manipur ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe planning commission of India is Mizoram. ",
            "keyString": "344351s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Parliament can legislate on matters listed in the state list:",
            "optionA": "  With the prior permission of the president ",
            "optionB": "  Only after the constitution is amended suit-ably ",
            "optionC": "  In case of inconsistency among state legislatures ",
            "optionD": "  At the request of two or more states ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tParliament can legislate on matters listed in the state list at the request of two or more states. ",
            "keyString": "344363s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Catharsis means discharge of emotions. A teacher can let off pent up energy of his disciple through",
            "optionA": "  Picnic/excursions ",
            "optionB": "  Mock- parliament ",
            "optionC": "  Celebration of festivals ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCatharsis means discharge of emotions. A teacher can let off pent up energy of his disciple through . Picnic/excursions, mock-parliament and celebration of festivals. ",
            "keyString": "344374s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Major limitation of mass communication is",
            "optionA": "  It is very costly ",
            "optionB": "  The feedback system is weak ",
            "optionC": "  More time is required to produce the message ",
            "optionD": "  The success largely depends upon the producer ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMajor limitation of mass communication is the feedback system is weak. ",
            "keyString": "344384s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Personalized system of education :",
            "optionA": "  Doesn't inculcate a feeling of socialization in students ",
            "optionB": "  Doesn't inculcate a feeling of competition ",
            "optionC": "  Leads to wastage of time and energy ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPersonalized system of education : doesn't inculcate a feeling of socialization in students, doesn't inculcate a feeling of competition, and leads to wastage of time and energy. ",
            "keyString": "377351s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important challenge before a teacher is :",
            "optionA": "  To maintain discipline in the classroom ",
            "optionB": "  To make students do their homework ",
            "optionC": "  To prepare question paper ",
            "optionD": "  To make teaching learning process enjoyable ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important challenge before a teacher is : to make teaching learning process enjoyable. ",
            "keyString": "377384s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If you are irritated and show rashness because of the inadequate behaviour of another teachers, what do you think about your own behaviour?",
            "optionA": "  It is justified because behaviours are echo lim ",
            "optionB": "  Your behaviour is not good because elders have the right to behave you in this way ",
            "optionC": "  Your behaviour is also a sign of maladjustment and so try to control yourself when you are maltreated ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYour behaviour is also a sign of maladjustment and so try to control yourself when you are maltreated. ",
            "keyString": "377397s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Teacher's professionalism means:",
            "optionA": "  The extent to which a teacher subscribes to a professional code ",
            "optionB": "  A teacher has to teach for the sake of getting salaries ",
            "optionC": "  A teacher must have completed professional teachers training course before his appointment ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher's professionalism means the extent to which a teacher subscribes to a professional code. ",
            "keyString": "377408s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the most fundamental of the guidance activities should be executed first?",
            "optionA": "  Determination of objectives ",
            "optionB": "  Selection of learning activities ",
            "optionC": "  Determination of learning process ",
            "optionD": "  Selection of curriculum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSelection of curriculum should be executed first. ",
            "keyString": "377419s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are the qualities of teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher should be able to arrange subject matter in a logical way ",
            "optionB": "  Teacher should inspire his pupil ",
            "optionC": "  Teacher should have sweet, polite and clear voice ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher should be able to arrange subject matter in a logical way, teacher should inspire his pupil and teacher should have sweet, polite and clear voice. ",
            "keyString": "410768s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The students who keep asking questions in the class",
            "optionA": "  Performs the role of an active member of the political party in power ",
            "optionB": "  Should be encouraged to participate in classroom discussion ",
            "optionC": "  Should be encouraged to find answer independently ",
            "optionD": "  Should be encouraged to continue questioning ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tShould be encouraged to find answer independently ",
            "keyString": "410796s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following one is most effective for a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Knowledge ",
            "optionB": "  Feedback ",
            "optionC": "  Management ",
            "optionD": "  Teaching skills ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeaching skills is most important. ",
            "keyString": "410808s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is the source of primary data?",
            "optionA": "  Books ",
            "optionB": "  Newspapers ",
            "optionC": "  Respondent ",
            "optionD": "  Reports ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRespondent is the source of primary data. ",
            "keyString": "410819s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Many experienced teachers go into a classroom and embark straight away upon a lesson. As a beginner to the teaching profession will you",
            "optionA": "  Adopt the same procedure ",
            "optionB": "  Make a written note of your preparation ",
            "optionC": "  As the students a like ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMake a written note of your preparation. ",
            "keyString": "410830s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All of the following are advantages of teaching machines except",
            "optionA": "  The control of cheating ",
            "optionB": "  Tracking of errors ",
            "optionC": "  The insurance of attention ",
            "optionD": "  Their universal use for different kinds of programmes ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the following are advantages of teaching machines except their universal use for different kinds of programmes. ",
            "keyString": "443616s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher can help adolescent to overcome his special problems, and help him to adjust to the environment. Which of the following attitude, he should not made?",
            "optionA": "  He should impart right information about sex ",
            "optionB": "  He should redirect the energies of the adolescent to fruitful channels through sports and other constructive activities ",
            "optionC": "  He should have unsympathetic attitude towards others ",
            "optionD": "  He should have right information about sex ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe should have unsympathetic attitude towards others. ",
            "keyString": "443644s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process of learning include which of the following",
            "optionA": "  Synthesis and organisation of the old and new experiences, resulting in a novel pattern ",
            "optionB": "  It includes all activities which leave permanent effect on the individual ",
            "optionC": "  In its simplest form, learning means acquisition, retention and modification of experience ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t All of these ",
            "keyString": "443656s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A new comer teacher who is maltreated in his class will deal with the students by",
            "optionA": "  Applying punitive measure ",
            "optionB": "  Improving his qualities and expressing it before them in a good way ",
            "optionC": "  Changing his class after consultation ",
            "optionD": "  Giving them a threat of expulsion ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImproving his qualities and expressing it before them in a good way. ",
            "keyString": "443666s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher can establish rapport with his pupil by",
            "optionA": "  Becoming a figure of authority ",
            "optionB": "  Impressing them with knowledge and skill ",
            "optionC": "  Playing the role of a guide with desire to help them ",
            "optionD": "  Becoming a friend to the pupils ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher can establish rapport with his pupil by playing the role of a guide with desire to help them.",
            "keyString": "443676s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Some students are weak in studies. What will be your attitude towards them?",
            "optionA": "  Strict ",
            "optionB": "  Lenient ",
            "optionC": "  Liberal ",
            "optionD": "  Lovable ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will have strict attitude towards them. ",
            "keyString": "476988s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a teacher is not able to answer the question of a pupil he should",
            "optionA": "  Say that he will answer after consultation ",
            "optionB": "  Rebuke the pupil ",
            "optionC": "  Say that question is wrong ",
            "optionD": "  Feel shy of his ignorance ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a teacher is not able to answer the question of a pupil he should say that he will answer after consultation. ",
            "keyString": "477016s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An individual's ability to learn is",
            "optionA": "  Acquired ",
            "optionB": "  Teachers ",
            "optionC": "  Elders ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn individual's ability to learn is elders. ",
            "keyString": "477029s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How will you demonstrate your impartial behaviour?",
            "optionA": "  By maintaining high self-esteem and egoistic behaviour ",
            "optionB": "  By making own behaviour more balanced and fair ",
            "optionC": "  By assaulting a teacher ",
            "optionD": "  By criticizing the teacher community ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy making own behaviour more balanced and fair. ",
            "keyString": "477040s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher who is not able to draw the attention of his students should",
            "optionA": "  Evaluate his teaching method and improve it ",
            "optionB": "  Resign from the post ",
            "optionC": "  Find fault in his pupils ",
            "optionD": "  Start dictating ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher who is not able to draw the attention of his students should evaluate his teaching method and improve it. ",
            "keyString": "477050s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Family is a means of",
            "optionA": "  Informal education ",
            "optionB": "  Formal education ",
            "optionC": "  Non-formal education ",
            "optionD": "  Distance education ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFamily is a means of informal education. ",
            "keyString": "509757s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There is tension among villagers and you are teacher there. What will you do?",
            "optionA": "  You will inform \"gram Pradhan\" ",
            "optionB": "  You will try to pacify them ",
            "optionC": "  You will report to police ",
            "optionD": "  You will keep distance from them ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will try to pacify them. ",
            "keyString": "509786s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher can develop social values among students by",
            "optionA": "  Telling them about great people ",
            "optionB": "  Developing sense of discipline ",
            "optionC": "  Behaving ideally ",
            "optionD": "  Telling them good stories ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher can develop social values among students by behaving ideally. ",
            "keyString": "509798s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What will you do in leisure time in school? You will",
            "optionA": "  Take rest in teacher's room ",
            "optionB": "  Read magazines in library ",
            "optionC": "  Talk to clerks in office ",
            "optionD": "  Check home work of students ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will check home work of students. ",
            "keyString": "509809s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher asks the questions in the class to",
            "optionA": "  Keep students busy ",
            "optionB": "  Maintain discipline ",
            "optionC": "  Attract student's attention ",
            "optionD": "  Teach ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher asks the questions in the class to attract student's attention. ",
            "keyString": "509819s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For better interaction with the students, the teachers objective should be the",
            "optionA": "  Equitable distribution of response time ",
            "optionB": "  Proximity ",
            "optionC": "  Affirm or correct student performance ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor better interaction with the students, the teachers objective should be the equitable distribution of response time, proximity and affirm or correct student performance. ",
            "keyString": "582942s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is quality of a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  He presenting the subject matter in an effective manner with clear explaining leading to better understanding of the matter ",
            "optionB": "  He should be trained to various teaching methodologies ",
            "optionC": "  He should know the child psychology ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above. ",
            "keyString": "582969s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In ancient education system, teachers applied some psychological principles in education especially to young child from pre-school age to adolescence. They recognize the role of",
            "optionA": "  Gurukul type of education ",
            "optionB": "  Convent system of schooling ",
            "optionC": "  Sense and perception in teaching and learning ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey recognize the role of sense and perception in teaching and learning. ",
            "keyString": "582982s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Recreational reading should be",
            "optionA": "  Reserved for the school library period ",
            "optionB": "  Assigned as homework ",
            "optionC": "  A responsibility of the home not the school ",
            "optionD": "  An integral part of language art curriculum ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRecreational reading should be an integral part of language art curriculum. ",
            "keyString": "582992s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which characteristic from the following is least concerned with a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Command over subject matter ",
            "optionB": "  Respect from college management ",
            "optionC": "  Good rapport with the students ",
            "optionD": "  Effective verbal communication ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRespect from college management is least concerned with a teacher. ",
            "keyString": "583003s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "You bringing your pupil for a monument visit outside your city. A father is reluctant to send his child for this. What will you do?",
            "optionA": "  Leave that child and go with others ",
            "optionB": "  Try to understand his father's problems ",
            "optionC": "  Try to convince him for sending his child by explaining the importance of such as educational and cultural trip ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTry to convince him for sending his child by explaining the importance of such as educational and cultural trip. ",
            "keyString": "615468s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The primary task of a teacher is :",
            "optionA": "  To teach the prescribed curriculum ",
            "optionB": "  To prepare students to pass their examination ",
            "optionC": "  To make them a thinking people ",
            "optionD": "  To modify their behaviour according to the needs of our society and country ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe primary task of a teacher is to modify their behaviour according to the needs of our society and country. ",
            "keyString": "615498s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who defined teaching as an organised system of specific activities aimed to help the learner learn something?",
            "optionA": "  Morrin ",
            "optionB": "  Byod ",
            "optionC": "  Smith ",
            "optionD": "  Jackson ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSmith defined teaching as an organised system of specific activities aimed to help the learner learn something. ",
            "keyString": "615511s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main role of education according to Plato is :",
            "optionA": "  To develop the power of contemplation ",
            "optionB": "  To develop the personality of each individuals ",
            "optionC": "  To strengthen the state ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "615522s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements regarding motivation is correct?",
            "optionA": "  Freewill, intellect and reason are the motivating factors according to Plato ",
            "optionB": "  Inborn, unlearned tendencies, called instincts are the motivating forces according to James Burt ",
            "optionC": "  Curiosity and level of aspiration are motivating factors according to Berlyne ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "615533s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "You have been selected in all the four professions given below. Where would you like to go?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher ",
            "optionB": "  Police ",
            "optionC": "  Army ",
            "optionD": "  Bank ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher ",
            "keyString": "649208s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What is most important while writing on blackboard?",
            "optionA": "  Good writing ",
            "optionB": "  Clarity in writing ",
            "optionC": "  Writing in big letters ",
            "optionD": "  Writing in small letters ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t A clean blackboard and a good handwriting are most important point to remember while using blackboards in classroom. Content should be visible to distant corner of the class. ",
            "keyString": "649236s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Some students send a greeting card to you on teacher's day. What will you do? You will",
            "optionA": "  Do nothing ",
            "optionB": "  Say thanks to them ",
            "optionC": "  Ask them to not to waste money ",
            "optionD": "  Reciprocate the good wishes to them ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSay thanks to them. ",
            "keyString": "649248s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A student comes late in your class. Then you will",
            "optionA": "  Inform to parents ",
            "optionB": "  Punish him ",
            "optionC": "  Try to know the reason ",
            "optionD": "  Not pay attention there ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhen students come to class late, it can disrupt the flow of a lecture or discussion, distract other students, impede learning, and generally erode class morale. Moreover, if left unchecked, lateness can become chronic and spread throughout the class. ",
            "keyString": "649260s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When the students become failed, it can be understood that",
            "optionA": "  The system has failed ",
            "optionB": "  The teachers failure ",
            "optionC": "  The text-books failure ",
            "optionD": "  The individual student's failure ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe individual student's failure. ",
            "keyString": "649270s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Institute of technology is situated at",
            "optionA": "  BHU, Varanasi ",
            "optionB": "  Osmania, university ",
            "optionC": "  Jamia Millia, Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tInstitute of technology is situated at BHU, Varanasi. ",
            "keyString": "681279s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the guidance of learning a teacher has many important roles. Which one of the following is the least important aspect of the teacher's role in the guidance of learning?",
            "optionA": "  The provision of continuous diagnostic and remedial help ",
            "optionB": "  The forestalling of habits ",
            "optionC": "  The provision of encouragement and moral support ",
            "optionD": "  The development of insight into what constitute the pitfalls and danger to be avoided ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe development of insight into what constitute the pitfalls and danger to be avoided. ",
            "keyString": "681307s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Feedback is",
            "optionA": "  Immediate reaction of receiver ",
            "optionB": "  Response of receiver to communicator's message ",
            "optionC": "  Analysis done by the receiver of the communicator's message ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFeedback is response of receiver to communicator's message. ",
            "keyString": "681319s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian institute of foreign trade is situated in",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Dehradun ",
            "optionC": "  New Delhi ",
            "optionD": "  Mumbai ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIndian institute of foreign trade is situated in New Delhi. ",
            "keyString": "681330s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not concerned with the duties of a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  To discipline the students ",
            "optionB": "  To prepare students for examinations ",
            "optionC": "  To make monthly and annual reports ",
            "optionD": "  To participate in extracurricular activities ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo participate in extracurricular activities. ",
            "keyString": "681340s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A statistical measure based  upon the entire population is called parameter while measure based on a sample is known as",
            "optionA": "  Sample parameter ",
            "optionB": "  Inference ",
            "optionC": "  Statistic ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA statistical measure based upon the entire population is called parameter while measure based on a sample is known as statistic. ",
            "keyString": "713938s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who said that members of the same species are not alike",
            "optionA": "  Darwin ",
            "optionB": "  Hebert spencer ",
            "optionC": "  Best ",
            "optionD": "  Good ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWho said that members of the same species are not alike Darwin. ",
            "keyString": "713966s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In order to augment the accuracy of the study the researcher",
            "optionA": "  Should increase the size of his sample ",
            "optionB": "  Should be honest and unbiased ",
            "optionC": "  Should keep the variance high ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn order to augment the accuracy of the study the researcher should increase the size of his sample, should be honest and unbiased and should keep the variance high. ",
            "keyString": "713978s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All are causes of no sampling errors except",
            "optionA": "  Faulty tools of  measurements ",
            "optionB": "  Inadequate sample ",
            "optionC": "  Non response ",
            "optionD": "  Defect in data collection ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll are causes of no sampling errors except inadequate sample. ",
            "keyString": "713989s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Survey study aims at",
            "optionA": "  Knowing facts about the existing situation ",
            "optionB": "  Comparing the present status with the standard norms ",
            "optionC": "  Criticizing the existing situation ",
            "optionD": "  Identifying the means of improving the existing situation ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSurvey study aims at comparing the present status with the standard norms. ",
            "keyString": "713999s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The validity and reliability of a research will be at stake when",
            "optionA": "  The author who is the source of information is biased, incompetent or dishonest ",
            "optionB": "  The incident was reported after a long period of time from that of its occurrence ",
            "optionC": "  The researcher himself is not competent enough to draw logical conclusions ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "747012s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the sample drawn does not specify any condition about the parameter of the population it is called",
            "optionA": "  Selected statistics ",
            "optionB": "  Distribution free statistics ",
            "optionC": "  Census ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf the sample drawn does not specify any condition about the parameter of the population it is called distribution free statistics. ",
            "keyString": "747041s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a primary source of data?",
            "optionA": "  Personal records, letters, diaries, autobiographies, wills etc ",
            "optionB": "  Official records, government documents, information reserved by socio-religious organizations ",
            "optionC": "  Oral testimony of traditions and customs ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "747054s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Collective psychology of the whole period is a theory which",
            "optionA": "  Can explain all phases of historical development ",
            "optionB": "  Means the psychology of the whole society ",
            "optionC": "  Means psychological  approach of the collection ",
            "optionD": "  All  of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCollective psychology of the whole period is a theory which can explain all phases of historical development. ",
            "keyString": "747064s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of a researcher?",
            "optionA": "  He is a specialist rather than a generalist ",
            "optionB": "  He is industrious and persistent in the trail of discovery ",
            "optionC": "  He is no inspirational to his choice of the field but accepts the reality ",
            "optionD": "  He is objective ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe is a specialist rather than a generalist. ",
            "keyString": "747075s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "When you make a mistake while teaching in the class and your students point it out angrily then what you does will?",
            "optionA": "  You will break all limits of anger ",
            "optionB": "  You will feel sorry for committing the blunder ",
            "optionC": "  You will scold him/her and resist them ",
            "optionD": "  You will leave the class for few days ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will feel sorry for committing the blunder. ",
            "keyString": "779188s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The project method of teaching is best associated with the philosophy of",
            "optionA": "  John Dewey ",
            "optionB": "  Max Rafferty ",
            "optionC": "  Robert Hatchins ",
            "optionD": "  ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe project method of teaching is best associated with the philosophy of John Dewey. ",
            "keyString": "779218s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In our present society where values are deteriorating, the excellent education will be which",
            "optionA": "  Enables one to earn in an easy manner ",
            "optionB": "  Exaggerates the competition in the society ",
            "optionC": "  Works for establishment of human and cultural value ",
            "optionD": "  Decelerates the social change in society ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExcellent education will be which works for establishment of human and cultural value. ",
            "keyString": "779230s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Emotional development is as much affected by maturation and learning as sensory processes, muscular growth and intellectual functions. Parlous experiment showed emotional responses could be learned through",
            "optionA": "  Conditioning ",
            "optionB": "  Imitation ",
            "optionC": "  Knowledge and skills ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmotional development is as much affected by maturation and learning as sensory processes, muscular growth and intellectual functions. Parlous experiment showed emotional responses could be learned through conditioning. ",
            "keyString": "779241s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Before starting instruction a teacher should",
            "optionA": "  Know the existing knowledge of his students and their background knowledge ",
            "optionB": "  Be aware of the environmental variables acting on the mind of the pupil ",
            "optionC": "  Be competent enough to arouse the curiosity of pupil ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "779252s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the final analysis, teaching must be thought of mainly as a process of",
            "optionA": "  Asking questions and evaluating the learning ",
            "optionB": "  Directing the activities of pupils ",
            "optionC": "  Hearing recitation of pupils ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn the final analysis, teaching must be thought of mainly as a process of directing the activities of pupils. ",
            "keyString": "811997s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher commands prestige, authority esteem and respect. He should make use of it through suggestion. He should not try to command respect through",
            "optionA": "  Scholarship ",
            "optionB": "  Punishing and creating revolting situation ",
            "optionC": "  Experience ",
            "optionD": "  Tact ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher commands prestige, authority esteem and respect. He should make use of it through suggestion. He should not try to command respect through punishing and creating revolting situation. ",
            "keyString": "812025s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher is successful only if he",
            "optionA": "  Knows his subject thoroughly well ",
            "optionB": "  Produces cent per cent result ",
            "optionC": "  Is approachable ",
            "optionD": "  Publishes papers in journals of repute ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher is successful only if he knows his subject thoroughly well. ",
            "keyString": "812037s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major responsibility with which the school personnel have been entrusted is that",
            "optionA": "  It harmonizes the child's need and demands of the society both ",
            "optionB": "  It makes the child able to get job ",
            "optionC": "  It prepares the school programme according to the need of the child ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major responsibility with which the school personnel have been entrusted is that it harmonizes the child's need and demands of the society both. ",
            "keyString": "812048s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of your students wants to share his problems with you. He visits your house for the same. In such a condition you should",
            "optionA": "  Suggest him to escape from his family ",
            "optionB": "  Extend necessary co-operation and boost his morale ",
            "optionC": "  Contact the student?s parent and solve the problem ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tExtend necessary co-operation and boost his morale. ",
            "keyString": "812058s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which can be described as an ideal teaching technique?",
            "optionA": "  Repetitive drill and rote memorization ",
            "optionB": "  Using props and manipulative to help students understand abstract concept ",
            "optionC": "  Encouraging in group discussion for logical thinking ",
            "optionD": "  Both 2 and 3 ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUsing props and manipulative to help students understand abstract concept and encouraging in group discussion for logical thinking. ",
            "keyString": "844649s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Quality of education in a school/college can be measured through",
            "optionA": "  Infrastructural facilities available ",
            "optionB": "  Manpower teachers and principal available ",
            "optionC": "  Students achievements ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "844678s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A mentally retarded student attends your lecture and sits in a deaf and dumb manner. What will you do?",
            "optionA": "  Make your lecture very simple and spare some extra time for him ",
            "optionB": "  You do not like to spoil majority for the individual ",
            "optionC": "  You pressurised the student to leave the class ",
            "optionD": "  You do not support him at all ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMake your lecture very simple and spare some extra time for him. ",
            "keyString": "844691s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Teaching in higher education implies",
            "optionA": "  Presenting the information given in the text book ",
            "optionB": "  Asking questions in the class and conducting examinations ",
            "optionC": "  Helping students prepare for and pass the examination ",
            "optionD": "  Helping students how to learn ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeaching in higher education implies helping students how to learn. ",
            "keyString": "844701s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For providing evaluative feedback to students, the teacher should",
            "optionA": "  Use correction, not criticism, in respect to inappropriate responses ",
            "optionB": "  Provide immediate feedback ",
            "optionC": "  Do not provide nonconstructive comments for evaluating activities ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "844711s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main aim of teaching is :",
            "optionA": "  To develop only reasoning ",
            "optionB": "  To develop only thinking ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  To give information ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main aim of teaching is to develop only reasoning and to develop only thinking. ",
            "keyString": "877557s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The quality of teaching is reflected :",
            "optionA": "  By the attendance of students in the class ",
            "optionB": "  By the pass percentage of students ",
            "optionC": "  By the quality of questions asked by students ",
            "optionD": "  By the duration of silence maintained in the class ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe quality of teaching is reflected by the quality of questions asked by students. ",
            "keyString": "877585s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The present annual examination system:",
            "optionA": "  Promotes rote learning ",
            "optionB": "  Does not promote good study habits ",
            "optionC": "  Does not encourage students to be regular in class ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe present annual examination system promotes rote learning, does not promote good study habits and does not encourage students to be regular in class. ",
            "keyString": "877597s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A college wants to give training in use of Statistical Package for Social Sciences (SPSS) to researchers. For this the college should organise :",
            "optionA": "  Conference ",
            "optionB": "  Seminar ",
            "optionC": "  Workshop ",
            "optionD": "  Lecture ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor this the college should organise a workshop. ",
            "keyString": "877608s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not the characteristic of a research?",
            "optionA": "  Research is systematic ",
            "optionB": "  Research is not a process ",
            "optionC": "  Research is problem oriented ",
            "optionD": "  Research is not passive ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch is not a process. ",
            "keyString": "877619s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A backward child is a slow learner. He does not respond satisfactorily to the ordinary school curriculum and to the usual methods. The causes of this phenomena are",
            "optionA": "  Poor intellectual ability and low intelligence ",
            "optionB": "  Physical defects and diseases ",
            "optionC": "  Emotional disturbance ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "911101s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "You are a teacher of literature. A chapter of a book deals with a biography of a scientist and his works. In this situation, what would you do with chapter?",
            "optionA": "  You would ask the students to read themselves ",
            "optionB": "  You would request the science teacher, to teach this chapter to the students ",
            "optionC": "  You would consult other books concerning with the scientist and then teach the lesson to student ",
            "optionD": "  Any one of them ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou would consult other books concerning with the scientist and then teach the lesson to student. ",
            "keyString": "911130s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "While delivering lecture if there is some disturbance in the class, then a teacher should",
            "optionA": "  Keep quiet for a while and then go on ",
            "optionB": "  Not bother of what is happening in the class ",
            "optionC": "  Punish those causing disturbance ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWhile delivering lecture if there is some disturbance in the class, then a teacher should keep quiet for a while and then go on. ",
            "keyString": "911143s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one is not the objective of special education?",
            "optionA": "  To pursue those curricular matters that strategically determine effective living for specific type of handicapped children ",
            "optionB": "  To develop motivational patterns in the handicapped that will produce achievements ",
            "optionC": "  To develop realistic self-concept in handicapped children ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "911153s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The introduction of career courses in schools and colleges aims at",
            "optionA": "  Developing the ability to make the intelligent choice of jobs ",
            "optionB": "  Providing professional knowledge to students ",
            "optionC": "  Increasing G.K. in students ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe introduction of career courses in schools and colleges aims at providing professional knowledge to students. ",
            "keyString": "911163s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher should keep his voice in the class",
            "optionA": "  High enough to be heard by every student clearly ",
            "optionB": "  Loud, so that everyone can hear clearly ",
            "optionC": "  Moderate ",
            "optionD": "  Sometime low and sometime high ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher should keep his voice in the class sometime low and sometime high. ",
            "keyString": "949978s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are true about teaching?",
            "optionA": "  The analysis and assessment of teaching provide feedback for further improvement in teaching method ",
            "optionB": "  It is highly dominated by communication skill ",
            "optionC": "  It is a process not an act ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above are true about teaching. ",
            "keyString": "950007s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is/are true about teacher/teaching?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher should have control over the students to maintain peace and order in the class ",
            "optionB": "  Teaching should be pupil centred rather than subject centred ",
            "optionC": "  Teacher should arouse interest among students about the subject ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above are true about teacher/teaching. ",
            "keyString": "950020s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about teaching/teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher should work as a leader in the class ",
            "optionB": "  Teacher should make a lesson plan before presenting lesson in the class ",
            "optionC": "  Teacher should maintain a democratic atmosphere in the class ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above are true about teaching/teacher. ",
            "keyString": "950032s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher learns maximum from",
            "optionA": "  Principal ",
            "optionB": "  Books ",
            "optionC": "  Students ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher learns maximum from students. ",
            "keyString": "950044s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All are examples of qualitative research except",
            "optionA": "  Religion and castes ",
            "optionB": "  Sex ",
            "optionC": "  Observation ",
            "optionD": "  Interest in the subject ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll are examples of qualitative research except interest in the subject. ",
            "keyString": "984369s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Area (cluster) sampling technique is used when",
            "optionA": "  Population is scattered and large size from which the sample is to be drawn ",
            "optionB": "  The population is heterogeneous? ",
            "optionC": "  A  long survey is needed ",
            "optionD": "  (a) and (c) both ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArea (cluster) sampling technique is used when population is scattered and large size from which the sample is to be drawn and a long survey is needed. ",
            "keyString": "984397s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "An example of scientific knowledge is",
            "optionA": "  Authority of the prophet or great men ",
            "optionB": "  Social traditions and customs ",
            "optionC": "  Religious scriptures ",
            "optionD": "  Laboratory and field experiments ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAn example of scientific knowledge is laboratory and field experiments. ",
            "keyString": "984410s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A researcher selects only 10 members from the total population of 50,000 as a sample. His research can be considered to be good if",
            "optionA": "  He was a good researcher ",
            "optionB": "  He was guided by his superior ",
            "optionC": "  The population was homogenous ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA researcher selects only 10 members from the total population of 50,000 as a sample. His research can be considered to be good if the population was homogenous. ",
            "keyString": "984421s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher encounters various problems during his professional career. He should",
            "optionA": "  Resign from his post in such situations ",
            "optionB": "  Do research on the problem and find a solution ",
            "optionC": "  Avoid the problematic situations ",
            "optionD": "  Take the help of the head of the institution ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher encounters various problems during his professional career. He should do research on the problem and find a solution. ",
            "keyString": "984431s35m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term phenomenology is associated with the process of",
            "optionA": "  Qualitative research ",
            "optionB": "  Analysis of variance ",
            "optionC": "  Correlational study ",
            "optionD": "  Probability sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term phenomenology is associated with the process of qualitative research. ",
            "keyString": "18296s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following methods serve to measure correlation between two variables?",
            "optionA": "  Scatter diagram ",
            "optionB": "  Frequency distribution ",
            "optionC": "  Two-way table ",
            "optionD": "  Coefficient of rank correlation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCoefficient of rank correlation serve to measure correlation between two variables. ",
            "keyString": "18325s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following phrases is not relevant to describe the meaning of research as a process?",
            "optionA": "  Systematic activity ",
            "optionB": "  Objective observation ",
            "optionC": "  Trial and error ",
            "optionD": "  Problem solving ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTrial and error is not relevant to describe the meaning of research as a process. ",
            "keyString": "18337s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not an example of a continuous variable?",
            "optionA": "  Family size ",
            "optionB": "  Intelligence ",
            "optionC": "  Height ",
            "optionD": "  Attitude ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHeight is not an example of a continuous variable. ",
            "keyString": "18348s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Action research means?",
            "optionA": "  A longitudinal research ",
            "optionB": "  An applied research ",
            "optionC": "  A research initiated to solve an immediate problem ",
            "optionD": "  A research with socioeconomic objective ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA research initiated to solve an immediate problem. ",
            "keyString": "18358s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following statements doesn't suit a teacher? ",
            "optionA": "  Really interested in students ",
            "optionB": "  Able to direct and discipline students ",
            "optionC": "  Reluctant to adapt himself to new situation ",
            "optionD": "  Enthusiastic about the work that teachers do ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tReluctant to adapt himself to new situation. ",
            "keyString": "54603s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Who can be a good teacher? ",
            "optionA": "  Whose students do not need to ask questions ",
            "optionB": "  Who answers all the questions asked by students ",
            "optionC": "  Who never encourages children to known something not in curriculum ",
            "optionD": "  Who always tells his/her students that from where they can get answers to their queries ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOme who answers all the questions asked by students. ",
            "keyString": "54633s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Meaningful learning takes place when",
            "optionA": "  Students are interested in topic taught ",
            "optionB": "  Explanations are given within reach of students ",
            "optionC": "  The new content being taught is related to the previous knowledge of the student ",
            "optionD": "  Students raise questions and get them clarified ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMeaningful learning takes place when students are interested in topic taught. ",
            "keyString": "54645s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Teachers use teaching aids for",
            "optionA": "  Making teaching interesting ",
            "optionB": "  Making teaching with understanding level of students ",
            "optionC": "  Making student attentive ",
            "optionD": "  The sake of its use ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeachers use teaching aids for making teaching with understanding level of students. ",
            "keyString": "54656s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about modern annual examination system?",
            "optionA": "  It encourages attaining knowledge by cramming ",
            "optionB": "  It doesn't encourage the habit of regular study ",
            "optionC": "  It doesn't encourage students to attain their classes regularly ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "54666s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "This methodology trains the child to search facts, rules and principles led by his own efforts, organize the set of knowledge gained and delineate general rule. The aforesaid statement is about which of the following methodology of teaching?",
            "optionA": "  Montessori ",
            "optionB": "  Kindergarten ",
            "optionC": "  Heuristic ",
            "optionD": "  Play way ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe aforesaid statement is about heuristic. ",
            "keyString": "111286s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "While dealing with juvenile delinquents a teacher should",
            "optionA": "  Play them filthy jokes ",
            "optionB": "  Talk with them frankly and guide and channelize ",
            "optionC": "  Complain to the principal against them ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTalk with them frankly and guide and channelize. ",
            "keyString": "111315s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a disadvantage of teaching machine?",
            "optionA": "  The insurance of attention ",
            "optionB": "  Their universal use for different kinds of programmes ",
            "optionC": "  The tracking of errors ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe insurance of attention is a disadvantage of teaching machine. ",
            "keyString": "111329s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The greatest important cause of failure in the beginning for a teacher lies in the area of :",
            "optionA": "  Interpersonal relationship ",
            "optionB": "  Verbal ability ",
            "optionC": "  Knowledge of the teacher ",
            "optionD": "  Light-handling of the student ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe greatest important cause of failure in the beginning for a teacher lies in the area of interpersonal relationship. ",
            "keyString": "111341s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best way to react to a wrong answer given by a student is :",
            "optionA": "  To scold him for not having learnt the lesson ",
            "optionB": "  To explain why the answer is wrong ",
            "optionC": "  To ask another student to give the correct answer ",
            "optionD": "  To ignore the wrong answer and pass on the next question ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo explain why the answer is wrong. ",
            "keyString": "111353s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The final result of a study will be more accurate if the sample drawn is",
            "optionA": "  Taken randomly ",
            "optionB": "  Fixed by quota ",
            "optionC": "  Representative to the population ",
            "optionD": "  Purposive ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe final result of a study will be more accurate if the sample drawn is representative to the population. ",
            "keyString": "148181s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Noise is known as",
            "optionA": "  Transmitting barrier ",
            "optionB": "  Receiving barrier ",
            "optionC": "  Sender barrier ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNoise is known as transmitting barrier. ",
            "keyString": "148208s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "UGC was established in",
            "optionA": "  1966 ",
            "optionB": "  1953 ",
            "optionC": "  1946 ",
            "optionD": "  1986 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOn 28 December 1953, Maulana Abul Kalam Azad (former Minister of Education) inaugurated University Grants Commission. 6. And in November 1956, UGC (University Grants Commission) was formally established as a statutory body of the Government of India via 'University Grants Commission Act, 1956' of the Parliament. ",
            "keyString": "148221s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Indian institute of natural resins and gums (formerly Indian lac research institute) is at ________",
            "optionA": "  Lucknow ",
            "optionB": "  Kolkata ",
            "optionC": "  Ranchi ",
            "optionD": "  New delhi ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIINRG, Indian Institute of Natural Resins and Gums is in Namkum, Ranchi. ",
            "keyString": "148232s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a teaching aid?",
            "optionA": "  Working model of wind mill ",
            "optionB": "  Tape recorder ",
            "optionC": "  16 mm film projector ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "148242s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The members of a group act, feel and think together, in a way which is different from the normal acting, feeling and thinking of individual, who come together to form the group. It is known as",
            "optionA": "  Memsis ",
            "optionB": "  Co-operation ",
            "optionC": "  Understanding ",
            "optionD": "  Group working ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe members of a group act, feel and think together, in a way which is different from the normal acting, feeling and thinking of individual, who come together to form the group. It is known as memsis. ",
            "keyString": "181511s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a good method of teaching?",
            "optionA": "  Lecture and dictation ",
            "optionB": "  Seminar and project ",
            "optionC": "  Seminar and dictation ",
            "optionD": "  Dictation and assignment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSeminar and project is a good method of teaching. ",
            "keyString": "181538s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the most important signal factor in underlying the success of beginning a teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Scholarship ",
            "optionB": "  Communicative ability ",
            "optionC": "  Personality and its ability to relate to the class and to the pupils ",
            "optionD": "  Organisational ability ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPersonality and its ability to relate to the class and to the pupils. ",
            "keyString": "181551s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is least required during the preparation of lecture?",
            "optionA": "  Clear introduction and summary ",
            "optionB": "  Time and control unit ",
            "optionC": "  Examples for better explanation and understanding ",
            "optionD": "  Factual materials in indirect way ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFactual materials in indirect way is least required during the preparation of lecture. ",
            "keyString": "181562s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In your view arrangement for education on environment in the school",
            "optionA": "  Is important for creating an awareness among an awareness among students about the environment ",
            "optionB": "  Is likely to put more burdens on students ",
            "optionC": "  Is a mode of entertainment for students ",
            "optionD": "  Is like giving work to teacher ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIn your view arrangement for education on environment in the school is important for creating an awareness among an awareness among students about the environment. ",
            "keyString": "181572s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why should you prefer teaching to other profession?",
            "optionA": "  For the service of humanity ",
            "optionB": "  For love of teaching ",
            "optionC": "  For love to young (youth) ",
            "optionD": "  For mastery over the subject of teaching ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor the service of humanity. ",
            "keyString": "216020s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The best way by a teacher to introduce a new subject by",
            "optionA": "  Giving a broad outline of the subject ",
            "optionB": "  Relating it to daily life situation ",
            "optionC": "  Relating it to previously studied subject or course material ",
            "optionD": "  Any of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe best way by a teacher to introduce a new subject by giving a broad outline of the subject, relating it to daily life situation and relating it to previously studied subject or course material. ",
            "keyString": "216050s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "As a teacher you should not demand your pupils which is beyond their stage of growth. If you do so, it only causes",
            "optionA": "  Frustrations ",
            "optionB": "  Frustrations, heighten tension and nervousness ",
            "optionC": "  Encouragement for more learning ",
            "optionD": "  Both (b) and (c ) ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a teacher you should not demand your pupils which is beyond their stage of growth. If you do so, it only causes frustrations, heighten tension and nervousness. ",
            "keyString": "216063s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher generally asks questions to his pupils during the lecture, why?",
            "optionA": "  Are students listening the lecture attentively ",
            "optionB": "  To know, which student is brilliant one ",
            "optionC": "  To know whether the students are understanding the lecture or not ",
            "optionD": "  To help the students ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo know whether the students are understanding the lecture or not. ",
            "keyString": "216074s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A competent teacher must have a sound knowledge in right order",
            "optionA": "  Practice, concept, theory and research ",
            "optionB": "  Theory, research, concept and practice ",
            "optionC": "  Concept, theory, practice and research ",
            "optionD": "  Research, practice, concept and theory ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA competent teacher must have a sound knowledge in right order: Concept, theory, practice and research. ",
            "keyString": "216084s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The adage of maintaining good relations with others is",
            "optionA": "  Sycophancy ",
            "optionB": "  Kaleidoscopic personality ",
            "optionC": "  Attractive features and mental make up ",
            "optionD": "  Control over emotion ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe adage of maintaining good relations with others is attractive features and mental make up. ",
            "keyString": "289010s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which is most favourable for education?",
            "optionA": "  Social class ",
            "optionB": "  Social mobility ",
            "optionC": "  Social stratification ",
            "optionD": "  Caste ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSocial stratification is most favourable for education. ",
            "keyString": "289054s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is most important for effective learning in classroom?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher's ability to create and maintain inappropriate responses ",
            "optionB": "  Provide immediate feedback ",
            "optionC": "  Do not provide unconstructive comments for evaluating activities ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher's ability to create and maintain inappropriate responses, provide immediate feedback and do not provide unconstructive comments for evaluating activities. ",
            "keyString": "289068s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the educational implication of the learning process?",
            "optionA": "  Memory ",
            "optionB": "  Interest ",
            "optionC": "  Curiosity and level of aspiration are motivating factors according to Berlyne ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "289080s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Use of telecast materials",
            "optionA": "  Enhances concentration and learning ",
            "optionB": "  Reduces the burden of the teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Increases retention power ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tUse of telecast materials enhances concentration and learning. ",
            "keyString": "289092s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of great importance in determining the amount of transference that occurs in learning is the",
            "optionA": "  IQ of teacher ",
            "optionB": "  Knowledge of the teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Use of appropriate elements ",
            "optionD": "  Presence of identical elements ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf great importance in determining the amount of transference that occurs in learning is the IQ of teacher. ",
            "keyString": "322911s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Democracy in the classroom is best reflected through",
            "optionA": "  Allowing students freedom to the observance of classroom rules and regulations ",
            "optionB": "  You will justify that most of the female students are more sincere towards their studies than male students. ",
            "optionC": "  You will justify to the male students that it is difficult for you refuse the request made by female students ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will justify that most of the female students are more sincere towards their studies than male students. ",
            "keyString": "322940s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For knowledge lessons",
            "optionA": "  Glover's scheme is used ",
            "optionB": "  Herbart's five-stage system is used ",
            "optionC": "  Garry's scheme is used ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor knowledge lessons Herbart's five-stage system is used. ",
            "keyString": "322953s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What can a teacher do to develop integrated personalities of his pupil?",
            "optionA": "  Children should be encouraged and helped to set themselves well-defined goals and objectives which they can hope to achieve ",
            "optionB": "  They should be helped to build their self-esteem to develop a sense of worthiness and positive ego image ",
            "optionC": "  Life in schools should be so planned that children are able to express themselves fully ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "322963s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following objectives of an elementary music programme the one of lowest priority is",
            "optionA": "  To expose children to a variety of musical compositions ",
            "optionB": "  To prepare children for wise use of leisure time ",
            "optionC": "  To develop a group of performers for holiday assemblies ",
            "optionD": "  To provide children with emotion outlets ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf the following objectives of an elementary music programme the one of lowest priority is to develop a group of performers for holiday assemblies. ",
            "keyString": "322974s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If majority of students in your class are weak you should",
            "optionA": "  Not care about intelligent students ",
            "optionB": "  Keep your speed in teaching fast so that student?s comprehension level may increase ",
            "optionC": "  Keep you teaching slowly ",
            "optionD": "  Keep your teaching slow along with some extra guidance to bright pupils ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf majority of students in your class are weak you should keep your teaching slow along with some extra guidance to bright pupils. ",
            "keyString": "357190s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The first important step in teaching is",
            "optionA": "  Planning of representation of topic or subject ",
            "optionB": "  Organizing the background of students for the subject ",
            "optionC": "  Organizing the material to be taught ",
            "optionD": "  Knowing the background of students ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first important step in teaching is knowing the background of students. ",
            "keyString": "357241s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Failure of students in examination, it may be the fault of",
            "optionA": "  Teacher ",
            "optionB": "  Principal ",
            "optionC": "  Students themselves ",
            "optionD": "  Both (a) and ( c) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFailure of students in examination, it may be the fault of teacher or students themselves. ",
            "keyString": "357258s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Research is born out of",
            "optionA": "  Human curiosity ",
            "optionB": "  Human requirements ",
            "optionC": "  Natural incidents ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch is born out of human curiosity. ",
            "keyString": "357270s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the first step of research?",
            "optionA": "  Identification of subject ",
            "optionB": "  Identification of nature of problem ",
            "optionC": "  Both 1 and 2 ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe first step of research is identification of subject and identification of nature of problem. ",
            "keyString": "357283s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Research is",
            "optionA": "  Searching again and again ",
            "optionB": "  Finding solution to any problem ",
            "optionC": "  Working in a scientific way to search for truth of any problem ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch is working in a scientific way to search for truth of any problem. ",
            "keyString": "389671s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A common test in research demands much priority on",
            "optionA": "  Reliability ",
            "optionB": "  Usability ",
            "optionC": "  Objectivity ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "389701s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is the first step in starting the research process?",
            "optionA": "  Searching sources of information to locate problem ",
            "optionB": "  Survey of related literature ",
            "optionC": "  Identification of problem ",
            "optionD": "  Searching for solutions to the problem ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIdentification of problem is the first step in starting the research process. ",
            "keyString": "389714s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To test null hypothesis, a researcher uses :",
            "optionA": "  T test ",
            "optionB": "  Anova ",
            "optionC": "  X2 ",
            "optionD": "  Factorial analysis ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo test null hypothesis, a researcher uses Anova. ",
            "keyString": "389725s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A research problem is feasible only when :",
            "optionA": "  It has utility and relevance ",
            "optionB": "  It is researchable ",
            "optionC": "  It is new and adds something to knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "389736s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Hypothesis cannot be stated in",
            "optionA": "  Null and question form terms ",
            "optionB": "  Declarations terms ",
            "optionC": "  General terms ",
            "optionD": "  Directional terms ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHypothesis cannot be stated in general terms. ",
            "keyString": "422768s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a successful communicator?",
            "optionA": "  One who presents material in a precise and clear way ",
            "optionB": "  One who is able to adapt himself according to the language of the communicate ",
            "optionC": "  One who knows a lot but is somewhat reserve in his attitude ",
            "optionD": "  One who sometimes becomes informal before the receiver and develops rapport ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne who knows a lot but is somewhat reserve in his attitude. ",
            "keyString": "422797s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a teacher had to establish his credibility in evaluating answer sheets he must be",
            "optionA": "  Strict ",
            "optionB": "  Lenient ",
            "optionC": "  Objective ",
            "optionD": "  Prompt ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a teacher had to establish his credibility in evaluating answer sheets he must be objective. ",
            "keyString": "422809s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Mainstreaming is a term associated with",
            "optionA": "  Career education ",
            "optionB": "  Education for handicapped ",
            "optionC": "  Inter-age class groupings ",
            "optionD": "  Environmental education ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMainstreaming is a term associated with educationfor handicapped. ",
            "keyString": "422820s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Suggestion helps in the development of information moral behaviour, aesthetic sense and character traits. Which of the following is the chief source of suggestions which would his life?",
            "optionA": "  Pupil of same age ",
            "optionB": "  Teachers ",
            "optionC": "  Elders ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tElders is the chief source of suggestions. ",
            "keyString": "422831s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "To gain popularity among students, teacher should :",
            "optionA": "  Personally help them in their study ",
            "optionB": "  Frequently organize tours ",
            "optionC": "  Dictate notes while teaching ",
            "optionD": "  Maintain good social relationship ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTo gain popularity among students, teacher should personally help them in their study. ",
            "keyString": "454957s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is not a quality of teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher should use modern techniques Methods and gadgets are teaching for better understanding of subject matter ",
            "optionB": "  Teacher should maintain an autocratic atmosphere in the class ",
            "optionC": "  He/she should have interest in his/her profession and knowledge must be updated ",
            "optionD": "  Teacher must be fair tin grading and marking ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tTeacher should maintain an autocratic atmosphere in the class. ",
            "keyString": "454987s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not true?",
            "optionA": "  Teaching is an art ",
            "optionB": "  Teachers can be trained ",
            "optionC": "  Teachers are born ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "454999s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The main function of educational psychology is to provide prospective teacher with:",
            "optionA": "  Research procedures for evaluating current teaching procedure ",
            "optionB": "  Insight into the needs, problems and styles of behaviour of teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Insight into various aspects of modern teaching education ",
            "optionD": "  How to deal with students and everyday class situation ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main function of educational psychology is to provide prospective teacher with: how to deal with students and everyday class situation. ",
            "keyString": "455011s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is not a quality of teacher?",
            "optionA": "  Teacher should be keen in his work and should be enthusiastic and anxious to keep his knowledge fresh and update ",
            "optionB": "  He should have feelings of love and sympathy ",
            "optionC": "  His language should be understandable to students ",
            "optionD": "  He may not know child psychology ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tHe may not know child psychology. ",
            "keyString": "455021s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The depth of any research can be judged by :",
            "optionA": "  Title of the research ",
            "optionB": "  Objectives of the research ",
            "optionC": "  Total expenditure on the research ",
            "optionD": "  Duration of the research ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe depth of any research can be judged by objectives of the research. ",
            "keyString": "504735s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Action-research is :",
            "optionA": "  An applied research ",
            "optionB": "  A research carried out to solve immediate problems ",
            "optionC": "  A longitudinal research ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAction-research is a research carried out to solve immediate problems. ",
            "keyString": "504767s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The basis on which assumptions are formulated :",
            "optionA": "  Cultural background of the country ",
            "optionB": "  Universities ",
            "optionC": "  Specific characteristics of the castes ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe basis on which assumptions are formulated is cultural background of the country. ",
            "keyString": "504782s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "We use factorial analysis :",
            "optionA": "  To know the relationship between two variables ",
            "optionB": "  To test the hypothesis ",
            "optionC": "  To know the difference between two variables ",
            "optionD": "  To know the difference among the many variables ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWe use factorial analysis to know the difference among the many variables. ",
            "keyString": "504794s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The experimental study is based on :",
            "optionA": "  The manipulation of variables ",
            "optionB": "  Conceptual parameters ",
            "optionC": "  Replication of research ",
            "optionD": "  Survey of literature ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe experimental study is based on the manipulation of variables. ",
            "keyString": "504805s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a child is a back bencher and unable to watch the blackboard clearly. As a result he stands, sees and sits repeatedly. What inference will you draw regarding the case?",
            "optionA": "  The child is of short height as compared to his classmates ",
            "optionB": "  The blackboard is under shining effect of light ",
            "optionC": "  The child has a defective-vision ",
            "optionD": "  Both (a) and ( c ) ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe child is of short height as compared to his classmates and the child has a defective-vision. ",
            "keyString": "537851s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is a characteristic of a researcher?",
            "optionA": "  He a specialist rather than generalist ",
            "optionB": "  He is industrious and persistent on the trail of discovery ",
            "optionC": "  He is not operational to his chosen filed but accepts the reality ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "537882s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The difference between experimental research and historical research in the process of",
            "optionA": "  The formulation of the hypothesis ",
            "optionB": "  The testing of hypothesis ",
            "optionC": "  Replication ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe difference between experimental research and historical research in the process of the formulation of the hypothesis, the testing of hypothesis and replication. ",
            "keyString": "537895s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The effective means in education communication is",
            "optionA": "  Black board writing ",
            "optionB": "  Audio-visual means ",
            "optionC": "  Audio means ",
            "optionD": "  Visual means ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe effective means in education communication is audio-visual means. ",
            "keyString": "537907s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The research is always",
            "optionA": "  Verifying the old knowledge ",
            "optionB": "  Exploring new knowledge ",
            "optionC": "  Filling the gap between knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe research is always verifying the old knowledge, exploring new knowledge and Filling the gap between knowledge. ",
            "keyString": "537918s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a girl student requests you to collect her posts at your address what would you like to do in this case?",
            "optionA": "  You would not give permission as it is against your own principles ",
            "optionB": "  You will never allow her suspecting a foul game ",
            "optionC": "  As a teacher you will allow her ",
            "optionD": "  You will permit her because you may get in touch with her ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAs a teacher you will allow her. ",
            "keyString": "570210s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most important task in teaching is",
            "optionA": "  Making monthly reports and maintaining records ",
            "optionB": "  Making assignments and hearing recitations ",
            "optionC": "  Directing students in the development of experience ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe most important task in teaching is directing students in the development of experience. ",
            "keyString": "570241s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The most accurate statement about teaching machines is that",
            "optionA": "  ",
            "optionB": "F. Skinner began the movement for their use ",
            "optionC": "  They were designed as an economy measure to replace teachers ",
            "optionD": "  They are not as efficient as teachers in reinforcing responses ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tB.F. Skinner began the movement for their use. ",
            "keyString": "570254s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The Dalton scheme of education is useful for which one of the following?",
            "optionA": "  For infants ",
            "optionB": "  For little children ",
            "optionC": "  For older children ",
            "optionD": "  For all of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe Dalton scheme of education is useful for older children. ",
            "keyString": "570265s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Why should a student not be punished severely?",
            "optionA": "  He may quarrel with a teacher ",
            "optionB": "  He may leave the school and join another ",
            "optionC": "  His parent may quarrel with the teacher ",
            "optionD": "  The student may develop a negative attitude towards his studies, teacher and school ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe student may develop a negative attitude towards his studies, teacher and school. ",
            "keyString": "570276s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of your colleagues is living in your locality but you have no affinity with him, the reason may be",
            "optionA": "  His selfishness ",
            "optionB": "  His religious faith ",
            "optionC": "  His social rejection ",
            "optionD": "  His miserable behaviour and rural background ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of your colleagues is living in your locality but you have no affinity with him, the reason may be his selfishness. ",
            "keyString": "619628s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A researcher wants to study the future of the congress-I in India. For the study which tool is most appropriate for him?",
            "optionA": "  Questionnaire ",
            "optionB": "  Schedule ",
            "optionC": "  Interview ",
            "optionD": "  Rating scale ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuestionnaire is most appropriate for him. ",
            "keyString": "619656s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "At present right to property is a",
            "optionA": "  Legal right ",
            "optionB": "  Human right ",
            "optionC": "  Fundamental right ",
            "optionD": "  Natural right ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAt present right to property is a legal right. ",
            "keyString": "619669s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Formulation of hypothesis may not be necessary in",
            "optionA": "  Survey studies ",
            "optionB": "  Fact finding (historical) studies ",
            "optionC": "  Normative studies ",
            "optionD": "  Experimental studies ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFormulation of hypothesis may not be necessary in fact finding (historical) studies. ",
            "keyString": "619680s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The carrier of mass communication is known as",
            "optionA": "  Mass media ",
            "optionB": "  Print media ",
            "optionC": "  Electronic media ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe carrier of mass communication is known as mass media. ",
            "keyString": "619690s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Nine year olds are taller than seven year olds. This is an example of a reference drawn from",
            "optionA": "  Vertical study ",
            "optionB": "  Cross-sectional study ",
            "optionC": "  Time series study ",
            "optionD": "  Experimental study ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNine year olds are taller than seven year olds. This is an example of a reference drawn from cross-section study. ",
            "keyString": "651388s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Ex post facto research means",
            "optionA": "  The research is carried out after the incident ",
            "optionB": "  The research is carried out prior to the incident ",
            "optionC": "  The research is carried out along with the happening of an incident ",
            "optionD": "  The research is carried out keeping in mind the possibilities?of an incident ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEx post facto research means the research is carried out after the incident. ",
            "keyString": "651417s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Research ethics do not include",
            "optionA": "  Honesty ",
            "optionB": "  Subjectivity ",
            "optionC": "  Integrity ",
            "optionD": "  Objectivity ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch ethics do not include subjectivity. ",
            "keyString": "651429s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is an indication of the quality of a research journal?",
            "optionA": "  Impact factor ",
            "optionB": "  H-index ",
            "optionC": "  G-index ",
            "optionD": "  I10-index ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tImpact factor is an indication of the quality of a research journal. ",
            "keyString": "651440s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Good 'research ethics' means",
            "optionA": "  Not disclosing the holdings of shares/stocks in a company that sponsors your research ",
            "optionB": "  Assigning a particular research problem to one PH.",
            "optionC": "/research student only ",
            "optionD": "  Discussing with your colleagues confidential data from a research paper that you are reviewing for an?academic journal ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGood 'research ethics' means assigning a particular research problem to one PH.D./research student only. ",
            "keyString": "651450s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Effective communication takes place when",
            "optionA": "  Source is attractive and authoritarian ",
            "optionB": "  Message design incorporates audience ",
            "optionC": "  Modern communication technologies are used ",
            "optionD": "  Receivers are passive recipient ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEffective communication takes place when message design incorporates audience. ",
            "keyString": "683472s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Memory protection is normally done by",
            "optionA": "  The operating system ",
            "optionB": "  The antivirus ",
            "optionC": "  The processor and the associated hardware ",
            "optionD": "  The user programme ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMemory protection is normally done by theprocessor and the associated hardware. ",
            "keyString": "683501s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In every field research pursuits promote systematic and gradual advancement of knowledge but discoveries are rare because",
            "optionA": "  Research is a continuous critical investigation ",
            "optionB": "  It is not common to be able to think beyond a grooved channel ",
            "optionC": "  Sustained experimental work needed for discoveries is not easily forthcoming ",
            "optionD": "  Most people lack depth of knowledge needed for it ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch is a continuous critical investigation. ",
            "keyString": "683513s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Students should prefer those teachers who",
            "optionA": "  Dictate notes in the class ",
            "optionB": "  Give important questions before examination ",
            "optionC": "  Can clear their difficulties regarding subject-matter ",
            "optionD": "  Are themselves disciplined ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tStudents should prefer those teachers who can clear their difficulties regarding subject-matter. ",
            "keyString": "683524s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What makes people to undertake research?",
            "optionA": "  Desire to face the challenge in solving the unsolved problems ",
            "optionB": "  Desire to get a research degree along with it consequential benefits ",
            "optionC": "  Desire to get intellectual joy of doing some creative work ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above ",
            "keyString": "683534s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A time bound testing programme for a students should be implemented in schools so that",
            "optionA": "  The progress of the students should be informed to their parents ",
            "optionB": "  A regular practice can be carried out ",
            "optionC": "  The students can be trained for final examinations ",
            "optionD": "  The remedial programme can be adopted on the basis of the feedback from the results ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe remedial programme can be adopted on the basis of the feedback from the results. ",
            "keyString": "716196s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The essential element of the syllabus for the children remained out of school should be",
            "optionA": "  Literacy competencies ",
            "optionB": "  Life-skills ",
            "optionC": "  Numerical competencies ",
            "optionD": "  Vocational competencies ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe essential element of the syllabus for the children remained out of school should be vocational competencies. ",
            "keyString": "716224s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The priority to girls education should be given because",
            "optionA": "  The girls are more intelligent in comparison than the boys ",
            "optionB": "  The girls are lesser in number than boys ",
            "optionC": "  The girls were badly discriminated in favour of boys in the past ",
            "optionD": "  Only girls are capable of leading for social change ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe priority to girls education should be given because only girls are capable of leading for social change. ",
            "keyString": "716236s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The success of integrated education depends on",
            "optionA": "  The support of community ",
            "optionB": "  The excellence of text-books ",
            "optionC": "  The highest quality of teaching-learning material ",
            "optionD": "  The attitudinal changes in teachers ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe success of integrated education depends on the excellence of text-books. ",
            "keyString": "716247s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The quality of schools education is exclusively depending upon",
            "optionA": "  Infrastructural facilities ",
            "optionB": "  Financial provisions ",
            "optionC": "  International support ",
            "optionD": "  The quality of teacher education ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe quality of schools education is exclusively depending upon the quality of teacher education. ",
            "keyString": "716257s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of research method is most appropriate when the focus of the research is subjective experience?",
            "optionA": "  Pre-empirical ",
            "optionB": "  Descriptive method ",
            "optionC": "  Experimental method ",
            "optionD": "  Qualitative method ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQualitative method is most appropriate when the focus of the research is subjective experience. ",
            "keyString": "748770s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The process of describing a culture or way of life from a folk people's perspective is",
            "optionA": "  Sociometry ",
            "optionB": "  Ethnomethodology ",
            "optionC": "  Ethnography ",
            "optionD": "  Photography ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEthnography is the process of describing a culture or way of life from a folk people's perspective. ",
            "keyString": "748801s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which type of research method is normally employed by the media?",
            "optionA": "  Secondary analysis ",
            "optionB": "  Content analysis ",
            "optionC": "  Unobtrusive measures ",
            "optionD": "  Natural experiment ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMedia research methods are the practical procedures for carrying out a research project. These methods include content analysis, surveys, focus groups, experiments, and participant observation. Research methods generally involve either test subjects or analysis of media. ",
            "keyString": "748816s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Oral history forms a part of which of the following methods of historiography?",
            "optionA": "  Private sources ",
            "optionB": "  Secondary sources ",
            "optionC": "  Running records ",
            "optionD": "  Recollections ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t Oral history forms a part of recollections. ",
            "keyString": "748828s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is also called archival data?",
            "optionA": "  Private sources ",
            "optionB": "  Secondary sources ",
            "optionC": "  Running records ",
            "optionD": "  Recollections ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPrivate sources is also called archival data. ",
            "keyString": "748839s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If the principal of your institution is not satisfied with your performance and charge you with the act of negligence of duties, how would you behave with him?",
            "optionA": "  You would take revenge by giving physical and agony to him ",
            "optionB": "  You would neglect him ",
            "optionC": "  You would take a tough stand against the changes ",
            "optionD": "  You would keep yourself alert and make his efforts unfruitful ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\t You would keep yourself alert and make his efforts unfruitful. ",
            "keyString": "781883s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following can be termed as most import task in teaching among the given?",
            "optionA": "  Directing students in development of experiences ",
            "optionB": "  Making monthly reports and maintaining records ",
            "optionC": "  Making assignments and checking worksheets ",
            "optionD": "  All of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDirecting students in development of experiences. ",
            "keyString": "781915s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If your own son is in your class. How will you behave with your students in comparison to your son?",
            "optionA": "  Just like your own son ",
            "optionB": "  Equal treatment is not possible to all the students ",
            "optionC": "  Repressed treatment ",
            "optionD": "  It is better to lend them a free hand ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tJust like your own son. ",
            "keyString": "781930s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The criteria for grading should be",
            "optionA": "  The material is covered in an accurate manner ",
            "optionB": "  The writing communicates clearly and effectively ",
            "optionC": "  Is there any originality in the submitted work ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above. ",
            "keyString": "781942s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Verbal guidance is least effective in teaching",
            "optionA": "  Attitude ",
            "optionB": "  Concepts and facts ",
            "optionC": "  Relationship ",
            "optionD": "  Skills ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tVerbal guidance is least effective in teaching skills. ",
            "keyString": "781953s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The test on the basis of which a teacher takes decision about the students is known as",
            "optionA": "  Performance test ",
            "optionB": "  Institutional test ",
            "optionC": "  Revision test ",
            "optionD": "  Instructional test ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe test on the basis of which a teacher takes decision about the students is known as performance test. ",
            "keyString": "814298s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In your institution, a debate test would be held shortly then how would you support your students?",
            "optionA": "  By writing the debate ",
            "optionB": "  You would tell students how to write a debate ",
            "optionC": "  You will tell students where to consult for literature ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will tell students where to consult for literature. ",
            "keyString": "814330s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is wrongly matched?",
            "optionA": "  Froebel - progressivism ",
            "optionB": "  Dewey - pragmatism ",
            "optionC": "  Skinner - gestalt ",
            "optionD": "  Herbart - apperception ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSkinner - gestalt is wrongly matched. ",
            "keyString": "814344s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "How can students in a class be made attentive?",
            "optionA": "  By speaking loudly in the class ",
            "optionB": "  By preparing your lecture properly ",
            "optionC": "  By creating curiosity in students ",
            "optionD": "  By wearing special types of clothes ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tArranging a question-answer session after each class which will make the students listen the whole time. Arrange different group activities and later emphasize on what you think was best in each cluster. And also create curiosity among students. ",
            "keyString": "814355s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher can get important place in society if he",
            "optionA": "  Performs the role of an active member the political party in power ",
            "optionB": "  Is scholar and in power ",
            "optionC": "  Participates actively in social activities ",
            "optionD": "  Performs his responsibility honestly ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher can get important place in society if he performs his responsibility honestly. ",
            "keyString": "814367s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A teacher exploits students in your school. In this situation, what you will do?",
            "optionA": "  Report the matter to the principal ",
            "optionB": "  Not interfere in this matter ",
            "optionC": "  Guide the teacher to please stop this activity ",
            "optionD": "  Go on satyagraha against the teacher ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tGuide the teacherto please stop this activity. ",
            "keyString": "863895s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Of the following learning theories, the one that embodies the idea that the learning takes place through insight is known as",
            "optionA": "  Gestalt ",
            "optionB": "  Stimulus-response ",
            "optionC": "  Connectionist ",
            "optionD": "  Pragmatic ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOf the following learning theories, the one that embodies the idea that the learning takes place through insight is known as gestalt. ",
            "keyString": "863924s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The teacher ought to know the problems prevalent in the field of education. The reason is that",
            "optionA": "  Only a teacher can do something about solving them ",
            "optionB": "  He can tell about the same to another teacher ",
            "optionC": "  Teachers can tell the government about it ",
            "optionD": "  With this knowledge, the teacher can have information about education ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe reason is that only a teacher can do something about solving them. ",
            "keyString": "863936s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The male students in your class are annoyed with you on the pretext you that have a favour to the female students. In such an embarrassing situation how would you like to control them in class?",
            "optionA": "  You will tell the male students that girls have no option except to depend on school teacher for their academic assistance ",
            "optionB": "  You will justify that most of the female students are more sincere towards their studies than male students ",
            "optionC": "  You will justify to the male students that it is difficult for you refuse the request made by female students ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will justify that most of the female students are more sincere towards their studies than male students. ",
            "keyString": "863947s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "With respect to the development of skills, all of the following are correct except that",
            "optionA": "  Pupil of same mental age should learn at the same rate ",
            "optionB": "  Group interaction increases the skills ",
            "optionC": "  Group instruction facilitates the learning process ",
            "optionD": "  Workbooks can be invaluable learning aid ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tPupil of same mental age should learn at the same rate. ",
            "keyString": "863958s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following languages can be the best medium of instruction at primary level?",
            "optionA": "  National language(Hindi) ",
            "optionB": "  International language(English) ",
            "optionC": "  Regional language ",
            "optionD": "  Mother tongue ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMother tongue is the best medium of instruction at primary level. ",
            "keyString": "896826s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "All of the following are the characteristic features of an effective teacher except",
            "optionA": "  Emphasis upon standards ",
            "optionB": "  Emphasizing group discussion for the purpose of clarifying the objectives ",
            "optionC": "  Emphasis upon the quick control of problematic situations ",
            "optionD": "  Differential treatment meted out to students of his class ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tEmphasis upon the quick control of problematic situations. ",
            "keyString": "896854s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following should a teacher adopt in his lecture in a class?",
            "optionA": "  Precise and low tone ",
            "optionB": "  Elongated tone ",
            "optionC": "  Precise and high tone ",
            "optionD": "  Moderate tone ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA teacher should adopt precise and low tone in his lecture in a class. ",
            "keyString": "896866s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is true about micro teaching?",
            "optionA": "  It is the following with video recording of lessons ",
            "optionB": "  It is a teacher education technique allowing teachers to apply clearly defined teaching goals ",
            "optionC": "  It is scaled down teaching encounters in class size and class time ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of the above. ",
            "keyString": "896877s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If students are not able to follow your lectures what will you do first?",
            "optionA": "  You will make your lecture easier ",
            "optionB": "  You will try to know the cause and find the right solution for that ",
            "optionC": "  You will start giving examples to them ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tYou will try to know the cause and find the right solution for that. ",
            "keyString": "896887s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The research that applies the laws at the time of field study to draw more and more clear ideas about the problem is :",
            "optionA": "  Applied research ",
            "optionB": "  Action research ",
            "optionC": "  Experimental research ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe research that applies the laws at the time of field study to draw more and more clear ideas about the problem is applied research. ",
            "keyString": "929280s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A research problem is not feasible only when :",
            "optionA": "  It is researchable ",
            "optionB": "  It is new and adds something to knowledge ",
            "optionC": "  It consists of independent and dependent variables ",
            "optionD": "  It has utility and relevance ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIt consists of independent and dependent variables. ",
            "keyString": "929309s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If a researcher conducts a research on finding out which administrative style contributes more too institutional effectiveness this will be an example of",
            "optionA": "  Basic research ",
            "optionB": "  Action research ",
            "optionC": "  Applied research ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tIf a researcher conducts a research on finding out which administrative style contributes more too institutional effectiveness this will be an example of applied research. ",
            "keyString": "929322s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Normal probability curve should be",
            "optionA": "  Positively skewed ",
            "optionB": "  Negatively skewed ",
            "optionC": "  Leptokurtic skewed ",
            "optionD": "  Zero skewed ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tNormal probability curve should be zero skewed. ",
            "keyString": "929333s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "A hypothesis is a",
            "optionA": "  Law  ",
            "optionB": "  Canon  ",
            "optionC": "  Postulate ",
            "optionD": "  Supposition ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tA hypothesis is a supposition. ",
            "keyString": "929344s36m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which kind of research sampling can be used to obtain a representative sample?",
            "optionA": "  Stratified sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Quota sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Systematic sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Simple random sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRepresentative samples are one type of sampling method. This method uses stratified random sampling to help identify its components. Other methods can include random sampling and systematic sampling. ",
            "keyString": "1737s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which sampling procedure gives each item an equal probability of being tested?",
            "optionA": "  Simple random sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Quota sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Stratified sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Systematic sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tRandom sampling is a part of the sampling technique in which each sample has an equal probability of being chosen. A sample chosen randomly is meant to be an unbiased representation of the total population. ",
            "keyString": "1765s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which sampling procedure involves grouping the population and then selecting the groups or the clusters rather than individual elements for inclusion in the sample?",
            "optionA": "  Area sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Cluster sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Multi-stage sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Deliberate sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tCluster sampling involves grouping the population and then selecting the groups or the clusters rather than individual elements for inclusion in the sample. ",
            "keyString": "1777s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which sampling is also known as purposive or non-probability sampling?",
            "optionA": "  Multi-stage sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Deliberate sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Area sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Sequential sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tDeliberate sampling is also known as purposive or non-probability sampling. ",
            "keyString": "1787s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which method implies the collection of information by way of investigator's own examination, without interviewing the respondents?",
            "optionA": "  Schedule method ",
            "optionB": "  Observation ",
            "optionC": "  Posting questionnaire ",
            "optionD": "  None of the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBy observation: This method implies the collection of information by way of investigator's own observation, without interviewing the respondents. ",
            "keyString": "1798s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Suppose you want to investigate the working efficiency of nationalised bank in India, which one of the following would you follow?",
            "optionA": "  Area sampling ",
            "optionB": "  Multi-stage sampling ",
            "optionC": "  Sequential sampling ",
            "optionD": "  Quota sampling ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tMulti-stage sampling should be followed. ",
            "keyString": "32614s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Controlled group condition is applied in",
            "optionA": "  Survey research ",
            "optionB": "  Historical research ",
            "optionC": "  Experimental research ",
            "optionD": "  Descriptive research ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tControlled group condition is applied in experimental research. ",
            "keyString": "32643s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which one of the following is a research tool?",
            "optionA": "  Graph  ",
            "optionB": "  Illustration ",
            "optionC": "  Questionnaire ",
            "optionD": "  Diagram ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tQuestionnaire is a research tool. ",
            "keyString": "32656s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Research is not considered ethical if it",
            "optionA": "  Tries to prove a particular point ",
            "optionB": "  Does not ensure privacy and anonymity of the respondent ",
            "optionC": "  Does not investigate the data scientifically ",
            "optionD": "  Is not of a very high standard ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tResearch is not considered ethical if it does not investigate the data scientifically. ",
            "keyString": "32667s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The research that aims at immediate application is",
            "optionA": "  Action research ",
            "optionB": "  Empirical research ",
            "optionC": "  Conceptual research ",
            "optionD": "  Fundamental research ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe research that aims at immediate application is action research. ",
            "keyString": "32677s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Bibliography given in a research report :",
            "optionA": "  Shows vast knowledge of the researcher ",
            "optionB": "  Helps those interested in further research ",
            "optionC": "  Has no relevance to research ",
            "optionD": "  All the above ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tBibliography given in a research report helps those interested in further research. ",
            "keyString": "66348s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Fundamental research reflects the ability to :",
            "optionA": "  Synthesize new ideals ",
            "optionB": "  Expound new principles ",
            "optionC": "  Evaluate the existing material concerning research ",
            "optionD": "  Study the existing literature regarding various topics ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFundamental research reflects the ability to expound new principles. ",
            "keyString": "66378s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The study in which the investigators attempt to trace an effect is known as :",
            "optionA": "  Survey research ",
            "optionB": "  Ex-post facto research ",
            "optionC": "  Historical research ",
            "optionD": "  Summative research ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe study in which the investigators attempt to trace an effect is known as ex-post facto research. ",
            "keyString": "66392s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "What do you consider as the main aim of inter disciplinary research?",
            "optionA": "  To bring out holistic approach to research ",
            "optionB": "  To reduce the emphasis of single subject in research domain ",
            "optionC": "  To over simplify the problem of research ",
            "optionD": "  To create a new trend in research methodology ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe main aim of inter disciplinary research to bring out holistic approach to research. ",
            "keyString": "66403s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "One of the aims of the scientific method in research is to :",
            "optionA": "  Improve data interpretation ",
            "optionB": "  Eliminate spurious relations ",
            "optionC": "  Confirm triangulation ",
            "optionD": "  Introduce new variables ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tOne of the aims of the scientific method in research is to improve data interpretation. ",
            "keyString": "66414s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "If majority of students in your class is weak you should",
            "optionA": "  Not care about intelligent students ",
            "optionB": "  Keep your speed of teaching fast so that students comprehension level may increase ",
            "optionC": "  Keep your teaching slow which can also be helpful to bright students ",
            "optionD": "  Keep your teaching slow along with some extra guidance to bright people ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tKeep your teaching slow along with some extra guidance to bright people. ",
            "keyString": "98470s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "For formulating the curriculum, which factor is most important?",
            "optionA": "  Teachers ability ",
            "optionB": "  Children's capabilities and needs ",
            "optionC": "  National ideology ",
            "optionD": "  Social and cultural ideals ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tFor formulating the curriculum, children's capabilities and needs is most important. ",
            "keyString": "98499s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "There are so many definitions of learning. Which of the following is most adequate?",
            "optionA": "  The modification of behaviour ",
            "optionB": "  The development of skills ",
            "optionC": "  The acquisition and organisations of knowledge ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe modification of behaviour is most adequate. ",
            "keyString": "98511s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Which of the following is meant of information collection?",
            "optionA": "  Schedule ",
            "optionB": "  Report ",
            "optionC": "  Plan ",
            "optionD": "  Scope ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tSchedule is meant of information collection. ",
            "keyString": "98523s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Teachers should study the educational philosophy because",
            "optionA": "  They do not know it ",
            "optionB": "  They do not have their own philosophy ",
            "optionC": "  Philosophy is the backbone of all disciplines ",
            "optionD": "  They may improve their work by clarifying their own philosophy ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThey may improve their work by clarifying their own philosophy. ",
            "keyString": "98533s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "In the income section, how many degrees (approx.) Should there be in central angle of the sector representing income tax?",
            "optionA": "  105 ",
            "optionB": "  120 ",
            "optionC": "  135 ",
            "optionD": "  150 ",
            "Answar": " Option B",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThere should be 120 degrees in central angle of the sector representing income tax. ",
            "keyString": "131376s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Water for civil supplies are commonly purified by",
            "optionA": "  Chlorination ",
            "optionB": "  Distillation ",
            "optionC": "  Filtration ",
            "optionD": "  Decantation ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tWater for civil supplies are commonly purified by chlorination. ",
            "keyString": "131404s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The term \"least restrictive environment\" refers to the education of the",
            "optionA": "  Handicapped ",
            "optionB": "  Gifted ",
            "optionC": "  Early childhood youngsters ",
            "optionD": "  Retarded ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe term \"least restrictive environment\" refers to the education of the handicapped. ",
            "keyString": "181425s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "According to Dewry, education is a :",
            "optionA": "  Social need ",
            "optionB": "  Personal need ",
            "optionC": "  Psychological need ",
            "optionD": "  Theoretical need ",
            "Answar": " Option A",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAccording to Dewey, education is a : social need. ",
            "keyString": "181457s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The teaching is not thought as a process of",
            "optionA": "  Directing the activities of people ",
            "optionB": "  Listening the recitation of pupils ",
            "optionC": "  Indoctrinating adult ideas to young people ",
            "optionD": "  None of these ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe teaching is not thought as a process of indoctrinating adult ideas to young people. ",
            "keyString": "181471s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "The major objective of education is:",
            "optionA": "  Reforming the society ",
            "optionB": "  Making students disciplined ",
            "optionC": "  developing inherent abilities/powers of students ",
            "optionD": "  Making students followers of teachers ",
            "Answar": " Option C",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tThe major objective of education is developing inherent abilities/powers of students. ",
            "keyString": "181483s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        },
        {
            "Question": "Each child grows in its own unique way. The wide individual differences are caused by",
            "optionA": "  Heredity ",
            "optionB": "  Endowment ",
            "optionC": "  Environmental influences ",
            "optionD": "  All of these ",
            "Answar": " Option D",
            "solution": " Solution:\t\tAll of these ",
            "keyString": "181494s37m27h16d15m7y2021",
            "isBookMark": 0,
            "isShown": 0,
            "isCon": 0
        }
    ]
}